神探夏洛克 前情提要
或者
神探夏洛克
-=圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/=-
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调&校对: 影子   特效: 皓瀚霏凡
翻译: 新人 小黄不小黄 凤梨酥
翻译: AU薇 波特妹子 cc 猫呗
根据阿瑟・柯南・道尔爵士原著改编
贝克
西路
可恶的新娘
立刻行动
来自司机的证言:
凶手是瑞可兰提夫人
西区的可怕谋杀
伊斯灵顿的惊人发现
幽灵身份被辨认出?
司机证言: 是瑞可兰提夫人
谁会是臭名昭著的
新娘谋杀案的下个受害人
苏格兰场被难住了
约翰・华生医生
如果方便的话
请立刻来一下
不方便的话
也来一下吧
福尔摩斯
第欧根尼俱乐部
保持安静
早上好 维尔德
我的哥哥在里面吗?
当然在的 先生
现在是早餐时间
在陌生人的房间?
是的 先生
这位先生是我的客人
啊 好的! 华生医生
我很喜欢看您写的"蓝宝石案"
谢谢 我... 很高兴... 你喜欢
你长得... 很丑
您说什么?
丑 你说的"蓝鱼贩子案"非常丑...
很高兴你喜欢我的土豆
华生 得多用功啊 你在舞蹈课上花的时间太多了
想我了吗?
尤斯塔斯・卡迈克尔之死
出租车司机的证词
凶手是瑞可兰提夫人
新娘又一次行凶
哈默斯诺子爵被杀
美好事业的肮脏结局
硫酸袭击案的著名受害人
苏格兰场毫无头绪
先姐艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提之墓
信念永存
1894年12月18日卒
红胡子
我叫夏洛克・福尔摩斯 地址是贝克街221B
The name's Sherlock Holmes and the address is 221B Baker Street.
- 午安  - 好吧
- Afternoon.  - Yeah.
他总是这副样子
He's always like that.
今天过得不太顺吗?
Bad day was it?
昨天你才搬进来跟他一起住 今天就和他一起破案了
Since yesterday you've moved in with him and now you're solving crimes together.
你看你这副高兴的样子 一点都不体面
Mwah! Look at you, all happy, it's not decent.
管它体面不体面呢 哈德森太太 游戏开局了!
Who cares about decent? The game, Mrs. Hudson, is on!
不要搞英雄崇拜 约翰
Don't make people into heroes, John.
英雄并不存在 就算存在 我也不在其列
Heroes don't exist and, if they did, I wouldn't be one of them.
我要让你下地狱
I will burn the heart out of you.
好了 这样应该就可以了
Right, this should do it.
- 你有穿裤子吗?  - 没
- Are you wearing any pants?  - No.
好吧
OK.
我就想你这样记住我 记住我是揍过/打败了你的女人
This is how I want you to remember me, the woman who beat you.
但其实根本就没有什么怪物
But there never was any monster.
夏洛克? 我们终于走到这步了
Sherlock? Here we are, at last.
- 再见 约翰  - 夏洛克!
- Goodbye, John.  - Sherlock!
那东西会要了你的命
Those things will kill you.
你这个混蛋!
Oh, you bastard!
追寻罪犯的快感令人血脉贲张
The thrill of the chase, the blood pumping through your veins,
你我二人对阵整个世界
just the two of us against the rest of the world.
等一下!
Wait!
我们得协调一致才行
We're going to need to coordinate.
我只向你再要一个奇迹
I asked you for one more miracle.
- 我要你不要死掉  - 我听到你的话了
- I asked you to stop being dead.  - I heard you.
闭嘴! 你才不是什么破案专家呢 从来都不是
Shut up! You are not a puzzle solver, you never have been.
你只是爱作秀!
You're a drama queen!
现在里面有个人就要死了
Now there is a man in there about to die.
游戏开局了 那就解决它!
The game is on, solve it!
他就是勒索界的拿破仑
He is the Napoleon of blackmail.
你这次当不了英雄了 福尔摩斯先生
No chance for you to be a hero this time, Mr. Holmes.
我是个高智商的反社会分子!
I'm a high-functioning sociopath!
无论把夏洛克
There is no prison in which
关进哪一所监狱
we could incarcerate Sherlock without
都会引起日常暴动
causing a riot on a daily basis.
但另一种选择 则需要征得您的首肯
The alternative, however, would require your approval.
致那些最好的时光 约翰
To the very best of times, John.
你想我了吗?
Did you miss me?
这怎么可能?
How is this possible?
- 流放生活过得如何?  - 我才走了四分钟
- How is the exile going?  - I've only been gone four minutes.
希望你已经吸取了教训
Well, I certainly hope you've learnt your lesson.
这次又是谁需要我了?
Who needs me this time?
想我了吗?
Miss me?
英格兰
England.
"第二次阿富汗战争予以多人荣誉和晋升
"The Second Afghan War brought honours and promotion to many.
但它带给我的只是不幸与灾难"
But, for me, it meant nothing but misfortune and disaster."
会没事的 上尉
All right, Captain.
"我拖着无法康复的身体回到了英格兰
"I returned to England with my health irretrievably ruined
未来一片黯淡
and my future bleak.
在这种情况下 我自然而然地选择了伦敦
Under such circumstances, I naturally gravitated to London.
这个帝国所有的闲散之人都被丢弃在了..."
That great cesspool into which all the loungers..."
- 华生!  - "这藏污纳垢之所 "
- Watson!  - "And idlers of the empire are drained."
华生!
Watson!
我是斯坦福啊
Stamford.
还记得我吗?
Remember?
之前巴茨医学院的同学
We were at Barts together.
当然记得 斯坦福
Yes, of course. Stamford.
天啊! 你这些年去了哪里?
Good Lord! Where have you been?
你都瘦得皮包骨了!
You're as thin as a rake!
好歹我还活着回来了 很多人可没我这么幸运
I made it home. Many weren't so lucky.
- 现在情况怎么样?  - 我需要一个住的地方
- So what now?  - I need a place to live.
要找一个看得上眼 价格还能承受的地方可不容易
Somewhere decent at an affordable price. It's not easy.
你知道吗 你是今天第二个对我说这话的人了
You know, you're the second person to say that to me today.
第一个是谁?
Hmm? Who was the first?
天啊
Good Lord.
显然他是在做实验啊
It's an experiment, apparently.
通过抽打尸体
Beating corpses to establish how long
观察死后淤青的存留时间
after death bruising is still possible.
- 这样做有什么医学上的目的吗?  - 不确定
- Is there a medical point to that?  - Not sure.
我也不知道 你说的那位朋友现在在哪里?
Neither am I. So, where's this friend of yours, then?
不好意思
Excuse me.
但愿我们没有打扰到你
I do hope we're not interrupting.
据我观察 你去过阿富汗
You've been in Afghanistan, I perceive.
这位是华生医生 这位是夏洛克先生...
Dr. Watson, Mr. Sherlock...
反应能力出色 你可以的
Excellent reflexes, you'll do.
不好意思 你说什么...?
I'm sorry...?
我看中了摄政公园附近的一套房子
I have my eye on a suite of rooms near Regent's Park.
我们可以一起租下来
Between us we could afford them.
房子? 谁说房子的事了?
Rooms? Who said anything about rooms?
我说了 我和他今天早上提过这件事
I did, I mentioned it this morning,
说我需要找人合租
I was in need of a fellow lodger.
然后他中午就携一个人出现了
Now he appears after lunch in the company
这个人有军队素养
of a man of military aspect
皮肤黝黑 最近负伤
with a tan and a recent injury, both suggestive
由此可以推断他参加了阿富汗战役 然后被强制退役
of the campaign in Afghanistan and an enforced departure from it.
结论就相当明显了
The conclusion seemed inescapable.
我们明天晚上继续探讨细节
We'll finalise the details tomorrow evening.
恕我先失陪了
Now, if you'll excuse me,
旺兹沃思有场绞刑 我要赶去参加
I have a hanging in Wandsworth and I'd hate them to start without me.
- 绞刑?  - 我有专业兴趣
- A hanging?  - I take a professional interest.
我还拉小提琴 抽烟斗 我想这些应该都不是问题
I also play the violin and smoke a pipe. I presume that's not a problem.
不是...
Er, no, well...
很明显你不介意被人插话
And you're clearly acclimatized to never getting
我们一定能好好相处的
to the end of a sentence. We'll get along splendidly.
那就定明晚七点
Tomorrow evening, seven o'clock, then.
我叫夏洛克・福尔摩斯
Oh, and the name is Sherlock Holmes
地址是贝克街221B
and the address is 221B, Baker Street.
没错... 他总是这副样子
Yes... he's always been like that.
报纸! 报纸!
Papers! Papers!
- "蓝宝石案"卖得怎么样?  - 非常畅销 华生医生
- Here, how's The Blue Carbuncle doing?  - Very popular, Dr. Watson.
下个月还会有谋杀案报道吗?
Is there going to be a proper murder next month?
我去找那些罪犯聊聊吧
I'll have a word with the criminal classes.
那就太好了
If you wouldn't mind.
那是他吗? 他在车上吗?
Is that him? Is he in there?
嗷! 不在
Ow! No.
不 不 他不在 回见
No, no, not at all. Er, good day to you.
走吧
Let on, walk.
圣诞快乐 福尔摩斯先生!
Merry Christmas, Mr. Holmes!
福尔摩斯先生!
Mr. Holmes!
你回家之前能不能先通知我一下!
I do wish you'd let me know when you're planning to come home!
我自己都不知道 哈德森太太
I hardly knew myself, Mrs. Hudson.
被肢解的乡绅就是这点不好
That's the trouble with dismembered country squires.
想和他们约时间见面太难了
They're notoriously difficult to schedule.
- 这里面是什么东西?  - 别管了
- What's in there?  - Never mind.
谢谢
Thank you.
你抓到凶手了吗 福尔摩斯先生?
Did you catch the murderer, Mr. Holmes?
抓到凶手了 但是还没找到受害者的双腿 算是平局吧
Caught the murderer, still looking for the legs. I think we'll call it a draw.
华生医生 我看到你又出版了一篇故事
And I noticed you've published another of your stories, Dr. Watson.
- 是的 你觉得好看吗?  - 不好看
- Yes, did you enjoy it?  - No.
是吗?
Oh?
- 你写的都不好看  - 为什么?
- I never enjoy them.  - Why not?
我好像什么话都没有 是吧?
Well, I never say anything, do I?
照你写的 我只会领人上楼 给你们做早饭
According to you, I just show people up the stairs and serve you breakfasts.
从叙事的角度看 笼统地讲 这些就是你的功能
Well, within the narrative, that is, broadly speaking, your function.
我的什么?!
My what?!
别以为就你一个不高兴 哈德森太太 那个讲狗的故事里我也没什么笔墨
Don't feel singled out, Mrs. Hudson, I'm hardly in the dog one.
"讲狗的"?
"The dog one"?
我是你们的房东 不是为情节服务的小配角
I'm your landlady, not a plot device.
你是说贝克斯菲尔德的猎狗?
Do you mean The Hound Of The Baskervilles?
而且这房子还被你搞得阴森森的
And you make the rooms so drab and dingy.
你去找那个插画师啊 他简直是在胡闹!
Oh, blame it on the illustrator, he's out of control!
我现在不留胡子别人还认不出我来了
I've had to grow this moustache just so people will recognise me.
"这么多年来 我很高兴能够记录我了不起的朋友
"Over the many years it has been my privilege to record
夏洛克・福尔摩斯先生的成就
the exploits of my remarkable friend, Mr. Sherlock Holmes,
有时候 我很难在他办过的那么多案子里
it has sometimes been difficult to choose which of his many
选出一件来呈现给读者
cases to set before my readers.
有一些故事还太敏感
Some are still too sensitive to recount,
还有些故事发生的时间离现在太近
whilst others are too recent in the minds of the public.
但在这些冒险故事里 只有一个案子让我的朋友
But in all our many adventures together, no case pushed my friend
在精神和身体上都走向了极端
to such mental and physical extremes
那就是可恶的新娘一案!"
as that of The Abominable Bride!"
天啊!
Good Lord!
哈德森太太 我的客厅里站着一个女人!
Mrs. Hudson, there is a woman in my sitting room!
你是故意的吗?
Is it intentional?
她是你的客户 我和她说了你不在家 她非要等你
She's a client. Said you were out, insisted on waiting.
你要不要坐下来说话?
Would you, er, care to sit down?
你问过她是来干什么的吗?
Didn't you ask her what she wanted?
你自己问啊!
You ask her!
你怎么没问她?
Why didn't you ask her?
我怎么问啊 书里的我不是没台词吗?!
How could I, what with me not talking and everything?!
天啊 随便给她几句台词吧 不然她得饿死我们!
Oh, for God's sake, give her some lines, she's perfectly capable of starving us!
下午好 我是夏洛克・福尔摩斯 这是我的朋友兼同事 华生医生
Good afternoon. I am Sherlock Holmes, this is my friend and colleague, Dr. Watson.
- 在他面前你可以畅所欲言 反正他也听不懂  - 福尔摩斯!
- You may speak freely in front of him, as he rarely understands a word.  - Holmes!
不过 你先别说话 让我来观察推理一下
However, before you do, allow me to make some trifling observations.
你有一种很顽皮的幽默感
You have an impish sense of humour,
你用这种幽默来减轻自己的痛苦
which currently you are deploying to ease a degree of personal anguish.
你最近和一个看上去很绅士的男人结了婚
You have recently married a man of a seemingly kindly disposition,
但是他离开了你
who has now abandoned you
去干一些莫名其妙的事情
for an unsavoury companion of dubious morals.
你最后的办法就是来到这里
You have come to this agency as a last resort,
想要和你的丈夫和好
in the hope that reconciliation may still be possible.
天啊 福尔摩斯!
Good Lord, Holmes!
当然这一切 我都是根据你的香水推断出来的
All of this is, of course, perfectly evident from your perfume.
她的香水?
Her perfume?
是的 她的香水 对我来说是个提示 对你则是灾难
Yes, her perfume, which brings insight to me and disaster to you.
为什么?
How so?
因为我认出来了 而你没有
Because I recognised it and you did not.
- 玛丽!  - 约翰
- Mary!  - John.
你怎么假装成顾客跑过来了?
Why, in God's name, are you pretending to be a client?
因为我只有这样才能见到我的丈夫 丈夫啊
Because I could think of no other way to see my husband, husband.
这可是让全世界的人都感兴趣的故事啊
It was an affair of international intrigue.
- 是一个乡绅被谋杀了而已  - 不管怎样 事情紧急
- It was a murdered country squire.  - Nevertheless, matters were pressing.
我不是不让你去 亲爱的 可是你一走就把我丢下了
I don't mind you going, my darling, I mind you leaving me behind.
可是你能做什么呢?!
But what could you do?!
那你又会做什么 不就是走来走去 记记笔记 做个惊讶的表情嘛?!
Well, what do you do, except wander around taking notes, looking surprised?!
够了!
Enough!
舞台已经搭好了 幕布也已经升起
The stage is set, the curtain rises.
我们可以开始了
We are ready to begin.
开始什么?
Begin what?
有时候想要破一个案子 得先把另外一个破了
Sometimes to solve a case, one must first solve another.
- 原来你手头上有案子 还是新的?  - 是老案子 很老很老的案子
- Oh, you have a case, then, a new one?  - An old one, very old.
我得往深处探索
I shall have to go deep.
深处? 什么深处?
Deep? Into what?
我自己
Myself.
雷斯垂德! 别待在门外了 进来吧
Lestrade! Do stop loitering by the door and come in.
- 你怎么知道是我?  - 听脚步声肯定没错
- How did you know it was me?  - The regulation tread is unmistakable.
你的比琼斯的轻 比格雷森的重
Lighter than Jones, heavier than Gregson.
我 我刚上楼... 哈德森太太现在好像都不说话了
I, I just came up... Mrs. Hudson didn't seem to be talking.
她已经开始用讽刺的方法进行文学批评了
I fear she has branched into literary criticism by means of satire.
现在的房东都喜欢这么干
It is a distressing trend in the modern landlady.
你不上班怎么跑到这里来了?
What brings you here in your off-duty hours?
- 你怎么知道我不上班?  - 自从你到这里
- How do you know I'm off duty?  - Well, since your arrival,
你百分之四十的时间都在看着我的酒瓶
you've addressed over 40% of your remarks to my decanter.
华生 给探长倒杯酒吧
Watson, give the Inspector what he so clearly wants.
雷斯垂德 你来干什么?
So... Lestrade, what can we do for you?
我不是为了公事来拜访的 我只是顺路经过
Oh, I'm not here on business, I just thought I'd drop by.
你只是随便来看看的?
A social call?
是啊 来给你们道一声节日快乐的
Yeah, of course, just to wish you the compliments of the season.
- 圣诞快乐  - 圣诞快乐
- Merry Christmas.  - Merry Christmas.
终于说完了
Thank God that's over.
探长 到底是发生了什么奇怪的事情
Now, Inspector, what strange happening compels you
让你来到我家 却觉得说出来有些尴尬呢?
to my door, but embarrasses you to relate?
谁说出事了?
Who said anything happened?
你说的 每一句简短的话语都有这个意思
You did. By every means short of actual speech.
等等 等等 福尔摩斯 你这次判断错了
Ah, ah, ah, ah, ah, Holmes, you have misdiagnosed.
那么 医生 请纠正我
Then, correct me, Doctor.
他并不是想要喝一杯 而是需要喝一杯
He didn't want a drink, he needed one.
他也并非感到尴尬 而是有些害怕
He's not embarrassed, he's afraid.
看来我的朋友也在学习嘛 进步还不小呢
My boswell is learning. They do grow up so fast.
华生 我们来帮他重拾苏格兰场的信心吧
Watson, restore the courage of Scotland Yard.
探长 请坐下说吧
Inspector, do sit down.
我... 我其实也不是害怕
I'm... I'm not afraid, exactly.
恐惧是面对危险时的智慧
Fear is wisdom in the face of danger,
没什么丢人的
it is nothing to be ashamed of.
谢谢
Thank you.
那么 请从头开始说吧
From the beginning, then.
你!
You!
别 求求你了!
No, please!
你呢?!
You?!
等一下
A moment.
这是什么时候的事?
When was this?
昨天上午
Yesterday morning.
人们是如何描述那位新娘的外表的?
The bride's face, how was it described?
"她的脸如死人般惨白 嘴唇鲜红如同流血的伤口"
"White as death, mouth like a crimson wound."
这是诗歌还是真相?
Poetry or truth?
很多人都会表示这俩是一样的
Many would say they're the same thing.
没错 你个笨蛋 但这是诗歌还是真相?
Yes, idiots. Poetry or truth?
那之后 我也亲眼看到了她的脸
I saw her face myself. Afterwards.
什么之后?
After what?
你?
You?
还是我?
Or me?
天啊 雷斯垂德 一个女人在大庭广众之下开枪自杀
Oh, really, Lestrade, a woman blows her own brains out in public
你竟然还需要我帮你找凶手?
and you need help identifying the guilty party?
苏格兰场的水准真是越来越没有底线了
I feel Scotland Yard has reached a new low.
我不是因为这个才来的
That's not why I'm here.
- 我猜也是  - 她叫什么 那个新娘?
- I surmised.  - What was her name, the bride?
她叫艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提 昨天是她的婚礼
Emelia Ricoletti. Yesterday was her wedding anniversary.
当然 有人报警了
The police, of course, were called.
她的尸体也被送到了停尸房
And her body taken to the morgue.
这是标准流程 你为什么要告诉我们显而易见的事?
Standard procedure. Why are you telling us what may be presumed?
因为后面的事与这有关
Because of what happened next.
这是几个小时之后 发生在莱姆豪斯的事
Limehouse. Just a few hours later.
他是艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提的丈夫 托马斯・瑞可兰提
Thomas Ricoletti. Emelia Ricoletti's husband.
或许他正要去停尸房认领遗体?
Presumably on his way to the morgue to identify her remains?
看起来没这个必要了
As it turned out, he was saved the trip.
# 请不要忘记我 #
# Do not forget me #
# 记住那个女孩... #
# Remember the maid... #
你是谁?
Who are you?
# 那个磨坊里的女孩... #
# The maid of the mill... #
你为什么要杀我? 你到底是谁!
Why are you doing this? Just tell me who you are!
亲爱的 你还记得我们的歌吗?
You recognise our song, my dear?
在我们的婚礼上 我还唱过呢
I sang it at our wedding.
艾米莉亚?
Emelia?
你... 你不是已经死了吗 你不可能还活着 你都死了啊!
You... you're dead, you can't be here, you died!
我漂亮吗 托马斯?
Am I not beautiful, Thomas?
是不是和你娶我那天一样漂亮?
As beautiful as the day you married me?
这到底是怎么回事?!
What the hell is all this about?!
小警员 你难道看不出来吗?
What does it look like, my handsome friend?
这是个有枪杀案的婚礼
It's a shotgun wedding.
直到死亡将我们分开 这案子里还来了两遍
Till death us do part. Twice in this case.
太神奇了
Extraordinary.
这不可能
Impossible.
真是精彩
Superb.
当街自杀 死人行凶 雷斯垂德 我们都要被你惯坏了
Suicide as street theatre, murder by corpse. Lestrade, you're spoiling us.
华生 去拿你的帽子和大衣吧
Watson, your hat and coat.
- 我们要去哪?  - 停尸房
- Where are we going?  - To the morgue.
一般不用着急去停尸房 不过这次我们一分钟都不能耽误
There's not a moment to lose, which one can so rarely say of a morgue.
我难道只能坐在这里吗?
And am I just to sit here?
当然不是 亲爱的 我们回来的时候肯定很饿
Not at all, my dear. We'll be hungry later.
等下 福尔摩斯 我难道要穿着苏格兰花呢外套去停尸房?
Holmes, just one thing, tweeds in a morgue?
华生 形势所迫 也只能这样了
Needs must when the devil drives, Watson.
再见 夫人
Ma'am.
- 要知道 我参加了运动  - 什么运动?
- I'm part of a campaign, you know.  - Oh, campaign?
- 女权运动  - 您是支持还是反对?
- Votes for women.  - And are you for or against?
出去
Get out.
哦 他们又都走了吧?
Oh, have they gone off again, have they?
真是不知道那些先生们过的是什么日子
I don't know, what a life those gentlemen lead.
是啊 那些先生们!
Huh, yes. Those gentlemen!
别担心了
Oh, never you mind.
我差点忘了 这是给你的
Oh, almost forgot, that came for you.
哦
Oh.
哈德森太太 请告诉我丈夫 我今天得晚些回家了
Mrs. Hudson, tell my husband I'll be home late,
我有点急事
I have some urgent business.
没出什么事吧?
Is everything all right?
没什么 就是有个朋友要我去帮忙
Oh, you know, just a, er, friend in need.
天啊 什么朋友?
Oh, dear. What friend?
英国
England.
这也太宽泛了
Well, that's not very specific.
今天是谁在停尸房值班?
Who's on mortuary duty?
- 你知道的  - 总是他
- You know who.  - Always him.
是哪个蠢货这么干的!
Please tell me which idiot did this!
这么做是为了大家的安全
It's for everyone's safety.
这个女人已经死了 她的半个脑袋都不见了
This woman is dead, half her head is missing.
她是不会带来任何危险的
She's not a threat to anyone.
跟她丈夫说这话吧 他就在那边 也已经死了
Tell that to her husband, he's under a sheet over there.
我认为 无论昨天晚上在莱姆豪斯发生了什么
Whatever happened in Limehouse last night, I think
我们都可以假定 那不是这个死去的女人干的
we can safely assume it wasn't the work of a dead woman.
有时候 就是会发生奇怪的事情
Stranger things have happened.
比如...?
Such as...?
比如... 就是奇怪的事情嘛
Well... Strange things.
你像个小屁孩一样胡说八道
You're speaking like a child.
这显然是人干的 他在哪?
This is clearly man's work. Where is he?
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
琥珀
Hooper.
说你呢 快去工作!
You, back to work!
猜你又跑来用小伎俩震惊我们了?
So, come to astonish us with your magic tricks, I suppose?
你有什么想引起我注意的事情吗?
Is there anything to which you would like to draw my attention?
完全没有 福尔摩斯先生
Nothing at all, Mr. Holmes.
你随时都可以走
You may leave any time you like.
琥珀先生 是我请福尔摩斯先生到这儿来合作办案的
Dr. Hooper, I asked Mr. Holmes to come here. Cooperate.
这是命令
That's an order.
有两个"很有意思的特征"
There are two "features of interest",
你在华生一身的故事里经常这么说
as you are always saying in Dr. Watson's stories.
我从没这么说过
I never say that.
实际上 你经常这么说的
You do, actually, quite a lot.
首先 这确实是艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提
First of all, this is definitely Emelia Ricoletti.
我们可以断定死者身份
She has been categorically identified.
毫无疑问 这就是她
Beyond a doubt, it is her.
那昨晚在莱姆豪斯的又是谁?
Then who was that in Limehouse last night?
那也是艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提
That was also Emelia Ricoletti.
不可能 她死了 就在这里
It can't have been. She was dead, she was here.
她丈夫在死前的几秒内 明确地辨认出了她
She was positively identified by her own husband, seconds before he died.
他没理由说谎 也不太可能弄错
He had no reason to lie, could hardly have been mistaken.
马车夫也认得她 毫无疑问就是她
The cabbie knew her, too, there's no question it's her.
但是她不可能同时出现在两个地方 对吧?
But she can't have been in two places at the same time, can she?
是的 华生 其中一个是刚死的人 活动范围非常有限
No, Watson, one place is strictly the limit for the recently deceased.
福尔摩斯!
Holmes!
- 有可能是双胞胎吗?  - 不可能
- Could it have been twins?  - No.
为什么不可能?
Why not?
因为从来不可能是双胞胎
Because it's never twins.
艾米莉亚不是双胞胎 她也没有姐妹
Emelia was not a twin, nor did she have any sisters.
她的哥哥四年前死了
She had one older brother who died four years ago.
嗯 有可能是那种秘密双胞胎
Hmm, maybe it was a secret twin.
什么玩意?!
A what?!
秘密双胞胎
A secret twin.
嗯? 你懂的?
Hmm? You know?
无人知晓的双胞胎
A twin that nobody knows about.
这整件事可能都被计划好了
This whole thing could have been planned.
从谋划的那一刻起吗 那她是得多有远见啊
Since the moment of conception. How breathtakingly prescient of her.
- 从来不可能是双胞胎 华生!  - 那你是怎么想的?
- It is never twins, Watson!  - Then what's your theory?
我就直说吧 你怎么了?
More to the point, what's your problem?
- 我 我不知道啊...  - 你这么害怕干嘛?
- I, I don't understand...  - Why were you so frightened?
目前没有任何证据显示是你弄坏了我的细颈瓶
Nothing so far has justified your assault on my decanter,
还有你为什么要让一个死掉的女人被捕呢?
and why have you allowed a dead woman to be placed under arrest?
还有一个很有意思的特征
Ah, that would be the other feature of interest.
她指尖上有一抹血迹
A smear of blood on her finger.
有很多种途径会造成这个结果
That could have happened any number of ways.
确实 还有一件事
Indeed. There's one other thing.
早些时候没有这血迹
It wasn't there earlier.
那个东西也是
Neither was that.
你!
You!
你?
You?
你?!
You?!
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
吞枪而死 子弹穿脑而过...
Gun in the mouth, a bullet through the brain...
脑后被打得干干净净
Back of the head blown clean off.
他怎么可能生还?
How could he survive?
你指的是"她"吧
"She", you mean.
不好意思?
I'm sorry?
不是"他" 是"她"
Not "he", "she".
当然
Yes, yes of course.
谢谢你们提供了这么一个迷人的案子
Well, thank you all for a fascinating case.
我破案之后会给你们发电报的 华生 走了
I'll send you a telegram when I've solved it. Watson.
枪伤绝对是致死原因
The gunshot wound was obviously the cause of death,
但还有一些值得推敲的地方
but there are clear indicators of consumption.
不妨验个尸
It might be worth a postmortem.
所有可能获得的信息我们都要拿到
We need all the information we can get.
顶头上司一走 他就变得这么有洞察力了!
Oh, isn't he observant, now that Daddy's gone!
我在某些方面还是很有洞察力的 正像福尔摩斯在其它方面特别瞎一样
I am observant in some ways, just as Holmes is quite blind in others.
真的吗?
Really?
没错 是真的
Yes, really.
真神奇... 一个人为了在男人的世界里出人头地竟能这么努力
Amazing... what one has to do to get ahead in a man's world.
他为什么那么说?
What's he saying that for?
快去工作!
Get back to work!
福尔摩斯? 你肯定已经有了些头绪了吧?
Well, Holmes? Surely you must have some theory?
还没有 水很深啊 华生 水很深
Not yet. These are deep waters, Watson, deep waters.
所以我得探得更深
And I shall have to go deeper still.
"直到好几个月后 我们才理出
"It was not for several months that we were to pick up
理出这诡异案子的头绪
the threads of this strange case again.
而且还是在让人意想不到的情况下"
And then under very unexpected circumstances."
五个人 全一样 毫无例外
Five of them now, all the same, every one of them.
嘘 拜托 这件事无比重要
Hush, please, this is a matter of supreme importance.
什么?
What is?
黄赤交角 我必须得搞明白
The obliquity of the ecliptic. I have to understand it.
是什么东西?
What is it?
我不知道 我正在努力搞懂
I don't know, I'm still trying to understand it.
我还以为你什么都知道呢
I thought you understood everything.
当然不是 那是对大脑空间的极大浪费 我只专攻一方面
Of course not, that would be an appalling waste of brain space. I specialise.
那这件事有什么可重要的?
And what's so important about this?
那这五起无聊的谋杀案有什么重要的?
What's so important about five boring murders?
不无聊啊 五个人死了 在家里被谋杀
They're not boring. Five men dead, murdered in their own homes, rice on the floor
地上像婚礼一样撒了米 墙上还写了血字"你"!
like at a wedding, and the word "You" written in blood on the wall!
是她啊 那个新娘 她又出现了
It's, it's her, it's the Bride. Somehow she's risen again.
- 破案了  - 不可能!
- Solved it.  - You can't have solved it!
当然可能了 非常简单
Of course I've solved it, it's perfectly simple.
神秘的瑞可兰提夫人事件
The incident of the mysterious Mrs. Ricoletti, the killer from
那个从坟墓里爬出来的凶手 被各大媒体争相报道
beyond the grave, has been widely reported in the popular press.
现在人们都用幽灵之为来伪装他们自己
Now people are disguising their own dull little murders as the
无聊的小谋杀 以迷惑愚蠢至极的苏格兰场
work of a ghost, to confuse the impossibly imbecilic Scotland Yard.
就是这样 案子破了
There you are, solved.
出门的时候去见哈德森太太一面 她喜欢多一点参与感
Pay Mrs. Hudson a visit on your way out, she likes to feel involved.
你确定?
You sure?
当然了 走吧 华生! 我准备好了
Certainly. Go away. Watson! I'm ready.
戴上帽子 穿好鞋子 我们有重要的约会要赴
Your hat and boots, we have an important appointment.
华生医生不是几个月前就已经搬走了吗?
Didn't Dr. Watson move out a few months ago?
好像是这样
He did, didn't he?
那我这段时间都是在和谁说话?
Who have I been talking to all this time?
我代表愚蠢至极的苏格兰场表示
Well, speaking on behalf of the impossibly imbecilic Scotland Yard,
那把椅子上肯定没有坐人
that chair is definitely empty.
是啊 对吧? 这样倒也没什么大碍
It is, isn't it? Works surprisingly well, though.
我本来还以为他有长进了呢
I actually thought he was improving.
你去哪里了?
Ah. Where have you been?
对不起 先生 今天早上我有点不在状态
Sorry, sir, I'm rather behind my time this morning.
你连鸡蛋都不会煮吗?!
Are you incapable of boiling an egg?!
这里的火一直都是灭着的 到处都是灰尘
The fires are rarely lit, there is dust everywhere
你在清洗我靴子的时候还差点把它刷坏了
and you almost destroyed my boots scraping the mud off them.
要不是因为和你们打交道是我妻子的事 我早就自己找你谈了
If it wasn't my wife's business to deal with the staff, I would talk to you myself.
我的妻子呢?
Where is my wife?
对不起 先生 夫人已经出门了
Begging your pardon, sir, but the mistress has gone out.
- 出门了? 这么早就出门了?  - 是的 先生
- Out? At this hour of the morning?  - Yes, sir.
您不知道吗 先生?
Did you not know that, sir?
她去哪里了? 她这段时间老是出门
Where did she go? She's always out these days.
您也差不多吧... 先生
Not unlike yourself... sir.
你说什么...?
I'm sorry...?
我只是比较会观察而已 先生
Just observing, sir.
够了 没人要你到处观察
Well, that's quite enough, nobody asked you to be observant.
对不起 先生 我只是想说你们两个最近很少同时在家了 先生
Sorry, sir, I just meant you're hardly ever home together any more, sir.
你越来越无礼了
You are dangerously close to impertinence.
我得和我妻子谈谈 让她要好好和你谈谈
I shall have a word with my wife to have a word with you.
很好 先生 您打算什么时候见她?
Very good, sir. And when will you be seeing her?
你给我听着...
Now, listen...
我差点忘了 先生 有您的电报
Oh, I nearly forgot, sir. A telegram came for you.
你忘了?!
You forgot?!
- 不 是我差点忘了  - 你一早上都在干点什么啊?
- No, I nearly forgot.  - What have you been doing all morning?
在杂志上读您新发表的故事啊 先生
Reading your new one in The Strand, sir.
你喜欢吗?
Did you enjoy it?
您为什么从来不写我 先生?
Why do you never mention me, sir?
下去吧
Go away.
- 什么交什么?  - 黄赤交角
- The what of the what?  - The obliquity of the ecliptic.
你让我赶紧过来 我以为是什么重要的事呢
"Come at once," you said. I assumed it was important.
是很重要
It is.
它是地球的赤道和太阳
It's the inclination of the earth's equator to the path of the sun
在黄道上的轨道的夹角
on the celestial plane.
你最近学习挺刻苦啊?
You been swotting up?
- 我为什么要这样?  - 为了让别人觉得你很聪明啊
- Why would I do that?  - To sound clever.
- 我本来就很聪明  - 我懂了
- I am clever.  - Oh, oh, I see.
你懂什么?
You see what?
我推断 我们要去见一个比你还聪明的人
I deduce we're on our way to see someone cleverer than you.
闭嘴
Shut up.
嘘...
Sh...
对不起 什么? 哦
Sorry, what? Oh.
这是最适合研究人类的地方了
To anyone who wishes to study mankind, this is the spot.
真不错 你真是越长越胖 背都粘在椅子上了
Handy really, as your ever-expanding backside is permanently glued to it.
- 早上好 哥哥  - 夏洛克 华生医生
- Good morning, brother mine.  - Sherlock. Dr. Watson.
你看上去... 气色不错
You look... well, sir.
真的吗? 我感觉我已经胖得不成样子了
Really? I rather thought I looked enormous.
说起这个 你吃这么多东西
Well, now you mention it, this level of consumption
实在是对你的健康不太好啊
is incredibly injurious to your health.
你的心脏...
Your heart...
- 这种事就不用担心了 华生  - 什么?
- No need to worry on that score, Watson.  - No?
他心脏的部位其实是空空如也
There's only a large cavity where that organ should reside.
- 我们家的人都这样   - 我又没有批评你的意思
- It's a family trait.  - Oh, I wasn't being critical.
如过你一直这样的话 先生 你最多再活五年
If you continue like this, sir, I give you five years at the most.
五年? 我们以为我只能活三年的 对吧 夏洛克?
Five? We thought three, did we not, Sherlock?
我还是感觉是四年
I'm still inclined to four.
一直都是这样 你会看 但是你不会观察
As ever, you see but you do not observe.
你看到我眼白部分的变色了吧
Note the discolouration in the whites of my eyes,
眼角膜附近的这圈脂肪
the visible rings of fat around the corneas.
是的 你说得对 我要改成赌你三年零四个月加十一天
Yes, you're right. I'm changing my bet to three years, four months and 11 days.
打赌?!
A bet?!
我知道你为什么不赞同 华生
I understand your disapproval, Watson,
但是如果他想要和我争的话 他想早点死完全是可以做到的
but if he's feeling competitive, it's perfectly within his power to die early.
- 这个险你就得自己冒了  - 你用自己的生命打赌?
- That's a risk you'll have to take.  - You're gambling with your own life?
这又怎么了? 这比用别的东西打赌有意思多了
Why not? It's so much more exciting than gambling with others'.
如果你吃那个布丁 我就赌你三年!
Three years flat, if you eat that plum pudding!
成交
Done.
我几天前就想和你见面 谈一谈庄园案的事情
I expected to see you a few days ago about the Manor House case.
我觉得你可能搞不定了
I thought you might be a little out of your depth there.
没有啊 我把案子破了
No. I solved it.
- 肯定是亚当吧  - 是的 是亚当
- It was Adams, of course.  - Yes, it was Adams.
都是嫉妒惹的祸 他给皇家天文协会写了一篇论文
Murderous jealousy. He'd written a paper for the Royal Astronomical Society
讲的是黄赤夹角
on the obliquity of the ecliptic,
然后他读到了一篇批评他的文章
and then read another that seemed to surpass it.
- 我知道 我读过了  - 你懂了吗?
- I know, I read it.  - Did you understand it?
懂了 我当然看懂了 它挺简单的
Yes, of course I understood it, it was perfectly simple.
不是 我是问你懂不懂嫉妒心
No, did you understand the murderous jealousy?
一个聪明的人很难想象一个比他更聪明的人
It is no easy thing for a great mind to contemplate a still greater one.
你叫我过来是专门羞辱我的吗?
Did you summon me here just to humiliate me?
是的
Yes.
当然不是 但这是最有趣的了
Of course not, but it is by far the greater pleasure.
那你能不能说清楚你叫我们来到底是...?
Then would you mind explaining exactly why you did summon..?
我们的生活正受到了一个看不到的敌人的威胁
Our way of life is under threat from an invisible enemy.
每天都在威胁着我们
One that hovers at our elbow on a daily basis.
这些敌人无处不在... 看不到... 也无法阻挡
These enemies are everywhere... undetected... and unstoppable.
社会主义者?
Socialists?
不是社会主义者 医生 不是
Not socialists, Doctor, no.
- 无政府主义者?  - 不是
- Anarchists?  - No.
法国人? 妇女政论者?
The French? The suffragists?
有没有不让你疑虑的人群啊?
Is there any large body of people you're not concerned about?
华生医生无比警觉 请详细说明...
Dr. Watson is endlessly vigilant. Elaborate...
不 调查
No. Investigate.
这是我的一个猜测 我需要你去证实
This is a conjecture of mine, I need you to confirm it.
我交给你一个案子
I'm sending you a case.
- 苏格兰人?  - 苏格兰人?!
- The Scots?  - The Scots?!
你知道最近那些关于
Are you aware of recent theories concerning what is
妄想症的理论吗?
known as paranoia?
像是塞尔维亚人
Oh, sounds Serbian.
一位女士会拜访你 卡迈克尔女士
A woman will call on you, Lady Carmichael.
我想让你接受她的案子
I want you to take her case.
但这些敌人 你不告诉我们他们身份的话
But these enemies, how are we to defeat them
我们又如何打败他们?
if you won't tell us about them?
我们不打败他们 我们很可能会输给他们
We don't defeat them. We most certainly lose to them.
为什么?
Why?
因为他们是对的 而我们错了
Because they are right. And we are wrong.
卡迈克尔女士女士的案子 是什么?
Lady Carmichael's case, what is it?
放心 这案子据对有趣
Rest assured, it has features of interest.
- 我从没用过这说法  - 你真的用过
- I never really say that.  - You really do.
那我猜 你早就破案了?
And you've solved it already, I assume?
只是猜想而已 我需要你们跑腿
Only in my head. I need you for the, er, legwork.
为什么不直接告诉我们你的答案?
Why not just tell us your solution?
那样还有什么意思?
And where would be the sport in that?
你愿意吗 夏洛克?
Will you do it, Sherlock?
我保证你会喜欢的
I can promise you a superior distraction.
只有一个条件 再吃一份李子布丁
On one condition. Have another plum pudding.
马上就会送来的
There's one on the way.
两年 十一个月 零四天
Two years, 11 months and four days.
哈 越来越有趣了! 滴答 滴答 滴答
Ha, it's getting exciting now! Ticktock, ticktock, ticktock.
谢谢你 维尔德
Thank you, Wilder.
一位梅拉斯先生想见您 福尔摩斯先生
Also, a Mr. Melas to see you, Mr. Holmes.
哦 给我五分钟时间 我有个赌要赢
Ah. Give me five minutes, I have a wager to win.
十五分钟才行
Better make that 15.
滴答
Ticktock.
福尔摩斯先生 我是来求取您意见的
Mr. Holmes, I have come here for advice.
- 这很容易  - 还有帮助
- That is easily got.  - And help.
这不总那么简单了
Not always so easy.
出事了 福尔摩斯先生 一些... 不寻常
Something has happened, Mr. Holmes, something... unusual
并且... 吓人的事
and... terrifying.
那你走运了
Then you are in luck.
走运?!
Luck?!
那些是我的专长 嗯 看起来很有意思啊
Those are my specialisms. Hmm, this is really very promising.
福尔摩斯...
Holmes...
请吧... 告诉我们何事让您如此烦心
Please... do tell us what has so distressed you.
我 我费心想了很久该怎么做
I, I thought long and hard as to what to do,
然后突然想到我的丈夫
but then it occurred to me that my husband was
与您的哥哥相识 或许通过他...
an acquaintance of your brother and that perhaps through him...
其实 我不确定这是否与您的领域相关 福尔摩斯先生
The fact is, I'm not sure this comes within your purview, Mr. Holmes.
哦?
No?
上帝保佑 我认为这可能该请教牧师
Lord help me, I think it may be a matter for a priest.
你上午作何打算 亲爱的?
And what does your morning threaten, my dear?
是开心地刺绣呢?
A vigorous round of embroidering?
还是在女帽商那里有个恼人的约会?
An exhausting appointment at the milliners?
我希望你是在说笑 尤斯塔斯
I hope you are teasing, Eustace.
怎么了?
What is it?
尤斯塔斯?
Eustace?
丹尼尔 索菲 出去玩吧
Daniel, Sophie, go out and play.
但是 妈妈...
But, Mama...
听妈妈的话 快去
Look, do as I tell you, quickly now.
尤斯塔斯 这是什么意思?
Well, Eustace, what does this mean?
死亡
Death.
什么?
What?
它意味着死亡
It means death.
呃 没什么 这没什么
Er, nothing, it's, er, it's nothing.
我... 误会了
I was... mistaken.
亲爱的 你脸色变得苍白
My dear, you've gone quite pale.
都说了没什么!
It's nothing!
- 尤斯塔斯...  - 信封您留着吗?
- Eustace...  - Did you keep the envelope?
我丈夫毁掉了 但信封是空的
My husband destroyed it, but it was blank.
没有名字地址什么的
No name or address of any kind.
告诉我 尤斯塔斯爵士去过美国吗?
Tell me, has Sir Eustace spent time in America?
- 没有  - 你们结婚前也没有?
- No.  - Not even before your marriage?
- 据我所知没有  - 嗯
- Well, not to my knowledge.  - Hmm.
请继续您的精彩讲述吧
Pray, continue with your fascinating narrative.
这件事发生在星期一早晨
Well, that incident took place last Monday morning.
两天后的星期三 我丈夫才第一次见到她
It was two days later on the Wednesday that my husband first saw her.
谁?
Who?
尤斯塔斯?
Eustace?
她来找我了 路易莎!
She's come for me, Louisa!
上帝啊 救救我 我的罪恶找上门来了!
Oh, God, help me, my sins have found me out!
谁来找你了? 尤斯塔斯 你吓到我了
Who's come for you? Eustace, you're frightening me.
快看 快看!
Well, look, look!
你没看到她吗?
Don't you see her?
没 我没看到有人
No, I see no-one.
走了
Gone.
你瞒了我很多秘密 这是另一个吗?
You keep so many secrets from me, is this another?
你看到谁了?
Who have you seen?
是她!
It was her!
是那个新娘!
It was the Bride!
而你什么也没看到?
And you saw nothing?
什么也没有
Nothing.
- 你丈夫有没有描述...?  - 没有 直到今天早晨
- Did your husband describe...?  - Nothing, until this morning.
尤斯塔斯?!
Eustace?!
尤斯塔斯?
Eustace?
尤斯塔斯?!
Eustace?!
该死!
Blast!
尤斯塔斯?!
Eustace?!
你在哪里? 是我啊!
Where are you? It's me!
# 请不要忘记我 #
# Do not forget me #
# 记住那个女孩 #
# Remember the maid #
# 那个磨坊里的女孩... #
# The maid of the mill... #
你是谁?
Who are you?
我命令你报上名来
I demand you speak, who are you?!
尤斯塔斯 看在上帝的份上 和我说话啊!
Eustace, speak to me. In the name of God!
她...
She's...
她是艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提
She is Emelia Ricoletti.
不 不要啊
No, not you.
不...
No...
求你了!
Please!
今夜 尤斯塔斯・卡迈克尔 你就会死掉!
This night, Eustace Carmichael, you will die!
- 福尔摩斯?  - 安静点 华生
- Holmes?  - Hush, Watson.
可是那个新娘 艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提
But Emelia Ricoletti, the Bride.
- 你知道她的大名?  - 你得原谅华生
- Well, you know the name?  - You must forgive Watson,
他就喜欢陈述明显的事实 对此近乎狂热
he has an enthusiasm for stating the obvious, which borders on mania.
请问一下你丈夫今天早上状态如何?
May I ask, how is your husband this morning?
他不愿意谈起那件事
He refuses to speak about the matter.
你也能想到 我把他赶出家门了
Obviously, I have urged him to leave the house.
不 他得待在原处才行
No, no, he must stay exactly where he is.
你不觉得他现在有危险吗?
Well, you don't think he's in danger?
当然 有人明显想要杀掉他 但这对我们有利
Oh, no, somebody definitely wants to kill him, but that's good for us.
舍不得孩子套不住狼
You can't set a trap without bait.
我的丈夫可不是诱饵 福尔摩斯先生
My husband is not bait, Mr. Holmes.
没错 但要是我们用对方法 他就能变成诱饵
No, but he could be if we play our cards right.
听着 你得马上回家
Now, listen, you must go home immediately.
我和华生医生会赶下一趟火车跟上
Dr. Watson and I will follow on the next train.
时间不等人 尤斯塔斯爵士今晚就要死了
There's not a moment to lose, Sir Eustace is to die tonight.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
我们应该... 大概可以救他吧
And we should... probably avoid that.
- 肯定  - 肯定可以救下他
- Definitely. - Definitely avoid that.
我的弟弟已经接下了这个案子
Little brother has taken the case, of course.
我现在需要你去打探情况
I now rely on you to keep an eye on things,
但绝不能让他发现你是跟我一伙的
but he must never suspect you are working for me.
明白了吗 华生?
Are you clear on that, Watson?
就交给我吧 福尔摩斯先生
You can rely on me, Mr. Holmes.
- 你不该...  - 我确实不该 你也一样
- You don't suppose...  - I don't and neither should you.
我话还没说完呢
You don't know what I was going to say.
你是想说这件事中可能有超自然的因素
You were about to suggest there may be some supernatural agency
而我打算嘲笑你一番
involved in this matter. And I was about to laugh in your face.
可是福尔摩斯 那位新娘艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提又出现了
But the Bride, Holmes, Emelia Ricoletti again.
已逝去的女人死而复生了
A dead woman walking the earth.
- 你真是让我惊讶 华生  - 是吗?
- You amaze me, Watson.  - I do?
你什么时候有的想象力啊?
Since when have you had any kind of imagination?
大概就从我让读者大众相信
Perhaps since I convinced the reading public that
某个没原则的瘾君子是个绅士英雄之后吧
an unprincipled drug addict was some kind of gentleman hero.
你既然说到了 我得说那确实挺了不起的
Yes, now you come to mention it, that was quite impressive.
不过你可以放心 这个世上并没有鬼
You may, however, rest assured there are no ghosts in this world.
除了一些我们自己闹出来的
Save those we make for ourselves.
你刚刚说什么?
Sorry, what did you say?
我们自己闹出来的鬼 是什么意思?
Ghosts we make for ourselves, what do you mean?
梦游症
Somnambulism.
你说什么?
I beg your pardon?
我会梦游 仅此而已 这是个再普通不过的症状了
I sleepwalk, that's all. It's a common enough condition.
你是个医生连这个都不知道!
I thought you were a doctor!
这一切都是个... 噩梦
The whole thing was a... bad dream.
你收到的那个信封里的东西也是吗?
Including the contents of the envelope you received?
那是个怪诞的恶作剧罢了
Well, that's a grotesque joke.
你给你的妻子感觉可不是这样 先生
Well, that's not the impression you gave your wife, sir.
- 她是个癔病患者 异想天开  - 不
- She's an hysteric, prone to fancies.  - No.
- 不好意思 你刚刚说什么?  - 我说她不是个癔病患者
- I'm sorry, what did you say? - I said no, she's not an hysteric.
她是位有着超凡洞察力的高智商女人
She's a highly intelligent woman of rare perception.
我的妻子看见一个橙子核都害怕
My wife sees terror in an orange pip.
你的妻子能看到别人看不到的世界
Your wife can see worlds where no-one else can see
还有其中有价值的东西
anything of value whatsoever.
真的吗?
Can she really?
那你是怎么"推断"出这个的呢 福尔摩斯先生?
And how do you "deduce" that, Mr. Holmes?
她嫁给了你
She married you.
所以我想她应该找到了特别的原因才是
I assume she was capable of finding a reason.
我今晚会尽全力救你一命
I'll do my best to save your life tonight, but first it would
但你最好先解释一下你和瑞可兰提案件的联系
help if you would explain your connection to the Ricoletti case.
瑞可兰提?
Ricoletti?
是的 请详细说明
Yes. In detail, please.
我从来没有听说过这个女人
I've never heard of her.
那就有意思了 我可从来没说过她是个女人
Interesting. I didn't mention she was a woman.
我们告辞了 但愿明天早上还能再见到你
We'll show ourselves out. I hope to see you again in the morning.
不可能了
You will not.
那就遗憾了 我就等着破你的谋杀案吧 日安
Then sadly I shall be solving your murder. Good day.
好歹你试过了
Well, you tried.
能麻烦你将这个交给卡迈克尔夫人吗 谢谢
Will you see that Lady Carmichael receives this. Thank you.
- 午安  - 没问题 先生
- Good afternoon.  - Certainly, sir.
那是什么东西?
What was that?
今晚卡迈克尔夫人
Lady Carmichael will sleep alone tonight,
会因为头剧痛而独睡
upon the pretence of a violent headache.
房子的所有门窗都会上锁
All the doors and windows of the house will be locked.
你觉得幽灵 不 新娘
Ha! You think the spectre, er, Bride,
会再来把尤斯塔斯爵士引诱到外面去吗?
will attempt to lure Sir Eustace outside again?
当然了 要不这威胁预告还有什么意思?
Certainly. Why else the portentous threat?
- "今夜你就会死掉!"  - 他肯定不会跟着她走的吧?
- "This night you will die!"  - Well, he won't follow her, surely?
很难说他究竟会怎样做
Hmm, it's difficult to say quite what he'll do.
- 愧疚正在啮噬他的灵魂  - 愧疚? 他有什么可愧疚的?
- Guilt is eating away at his soul.  - Guilt? About what?
他对过去的事心怀愧疚 那些橙子核让他想起了过去
Something in his past. The orange pips were a reminder.
- 那不是个恶作剧吗?  - 根本不是
- Not a joke?  - Not at all.
橙子核是一种用来预示复仇死亡的经典方法 源于美国
Orange pips are a traditional warning of avenging death, originating in America.
尤斯塔斯爵士非常了解这一点
Sir Eustace knows this only too well,
他也知道自己要受到惩罚了
just as he knows why he is to be punished.
这和艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提有什么关系吗?
Something to do with Emelia Ricoletti?
我想是的 人人都有不堪的过去 华生 至于鬼魂
I presume. We all have a past, Watson. Ghosts.
他们是为了衬托那些阳光灿烂的日子而存在的阴霾
They are the shadows that define our every sunny day.
尤斯塔斯爵士知道他已经被盯上了
Sir Eustace knows he's a marked man.
他所恐惧的绝不是有人想谋杀他那么简单
There's something more than murder he fears.
他对自己将要被瑞可兰提夫人死而复生的亡灵
He believes he is to be dragged to hell by the risen corpse
拖入地狱这件事情深信不疑
of the late Mrs. Ricoletti.
刚才纯粹是胡说 对吧?
That's a lot of nonsense, isn't it?
当然啦 你带左轮枪了吗?
God, yes. Did you bring your revolver?
对付鬼魂 左轮枪有什么用?
What good would that be against a ghost?
- 是没用 那你带了吗?  - 带了 当然带了
- Exactly. Did you bring it?  - Yeah, of course.
那就来吧 华生 来吧 游戏已经开始了
Then come, Watson, come. The game is afoot.
- 坐下 华生 真是的!  - 对不起 我有点抽筋
- Get down, Watson, for heaven's sake!  - Sorry. Cramp.
- 灯还点着吗?  - 是的
- Is the lamp still burning?  - Yes.
尤斯塔斯爵士睡下了
There goes Sir Eustace.
卡迈克尔女士也是
And Lady Carmichael.
整个屋子都睡了
The house sleeps.
上帝啊 这绝对是我这辈子度过的最漫长的夜晚
Hmm, good God, this is the longest night of my life.
耐心点 华生
Have patience, Watson.
才刚十二点
Only midnight.
我发现 我们很少一起这么坐着
You know, it's rare for us to sit together like this.
说得没错 这姿势对膝盖非常不好
I should hope so. It's murder on the knees.
两个老朋友说说话 闲聊几句
Two old friends just talking. Chewing the fat.
男人之间的对话
Man-to-man.
看起来 这个女人很值得尊敬
So, a remarkable woman.
- 哪个?  - 卡迈克尔女士
- Who?  - Lady Carmichael.
女性这个方面一直是你的专长 华生
The fair sex is your department, Watson.
所以我就相信你说的
I'll take your word for it.
你喜欢她这种类型的 "一个具有超凡洞察力的女人"
Well, you liked her. "A woman of rare perception."
还有非常高的足弓 我从她进屋的步伐里注意到这点
And admirably high arches. I noticed them as soon as she stepped into the room.
- 是的 我觉得他配不上她  - 你也这么觉得吗?
- Huh, she's far too good for him.  - You think so?
不 但你是这么想的 我看得出来
No. You think so. I could tell.
恰恰相反 我在这件事情上不抱任何观点
On the contrary, I have no view on the matter.
你绝对有
Yes, you have.
- 我并不会细想婚姻的问题  - 为什么?
- Marriage is not a subject upon which I dwell.  - Oh, why not?
你今天晚上是怎么了?
What's the matter with you this evening?
你带着的那块怀表 表盖里面有一张照片
That watch that you're wearing, there's a photograph inside it.
我有一次不小心看到了 我相信那应该是艾琳・艾德勒
I glimpsed it once. I believe it is of Irene Adler.
你那不叫不小心看到 你是蓄意等到我睡着了
You didn't glimpse it, you waited till I'd fallen asleep
- 然后翻出来看的  - 好吧 没错
- and looked at it.  - Yes, I did.
- 你真的以为我不会发现吗?  - 艾琳・艾德勒
- You seriously thought I wouldn't notice?  - Irene Adler.
值得尊敬的对手 非同寻常的经历
Formidable opponent, a remarkable adventure.
- 还有心旷神怡的照片  - 你为什么用这种口气说话?
- A very nice photograph.  - Why are you talking like this?
- 你为什么坚决要一直单身呢?  - 你没毛病吧 华生?
- Why are you so determined to be alone?  - Are you quite well, Watson?
- 这个问题很奇怪吗?  - 如果是个维也纳精神病医生问 不奇怪
- Is it such a curious question?  - From a Viennese alienist, no.
但是从一个退役的军医嘴里问出来 非常奇怪
From a retired Army surgeon, most certainly.
福尔摩斯 应该没人能反驳这一点
Holmes, against absolutely no opposition whatsoever,
- 我是你最好的朋友  - 我同意这点
- I am your closest friend.  - I concede it.
现在我正尝试着和你
I am currently attempting to have
用一种非常正常的方式对话
a perfectly normal conversation with you.
- 别这样说话  - 你为什么要一直单身呢?
- Please don't.  - Why do you need to be alone?
如果你指的是个人情感纠葛方面的事情 华生
If you are referring to romantic entanglement, Watson,
我觉得你就是 那么我以前经常这么解释
which I rather fear you are, as I have often explained before,
我厌恶所有的情感
all emotion is abhorrent to me.
就像精密仪器里漏进的沙子
It is the grit in a sensitive instrument.
- 透镜上的裂痕一样  - 透镜里的裂痕 没错
- The crack in the lens.  - The crack in the lens. Yes.
既然这样 看吧 我早就告诉过你
Well, there you are, you see, I've said it all before.
不 那些是我写的
No, I wrote all that.
你在引用杂志上刊登的小说里的"你"说的话
You're quoting yourself from The Strand Magazine.
- 是啊 没错  - 那些是我说的 不是你说的!
- Well, exactly.  - Those are my words, not yours!
那是我向公众展现的你 不是真正的你
That is the version of you that I present to the public.
没有人性的大脑 精妙的计算机器
The brain without a heart. The calculating machine.
那些都是我社稷出来的 福尔摩斯 读者们愿意接受这个
I write all of that, Holmes, and the readers lap it up.
但我不相信你是这样的人
But I do not believe it.
好吧 那我应该得写信告诉你的编辑
Well, I've a good mind to write to your editor.
你是个活生生的 会喘气的人
You are a living, breathing man.
- 你也有自己的生活 自己的过去  - 什么?
- You've lived a life, you have a past.  - A what?!
- 你肯定有过一个...  - 有过什么?
- Well, you must have had...  - Had what?
- 你懂的  - 不懂
- You know.  - No.
一些经验
Experiences.
把你的手枪给我 我突然觉得需要用一下
Pass me your revolver, I have a sudden need to use it.
该死的 福尔摩斯 你也有血有肉 有感情 你有...
Damn it, Holmes, you are flesh and blood, you have feelings, you have...
你肯定有... 某些冲动
You must have... impulses.
天啊 我从没这么急切地想被杀人鬼袭击了
Dear Lord, I have never been so impatient to be attacked by a murderous ghost.
作为你的朋友 作为一个关心你的人...
As your friend, as someone who worries about you...
是什么把你变成这样的?
what made you like this?
哦 华生...
Oh, Watson...
没有人能改变我
Nothing made me.
我就是我
I made me.
红胡子?
Redbeard?
上帝啊!
Good God!
我们该怎么办?
What are we to do?
我们去和她聊聊吧
Why don't we have a chat?
瑞可兰提夫人 是你吧!
Mrs. Ricoletti, I believe!
真是个令人愉快的夜晚啊 不是吗?
A pleasant night for the time of year, is it not?
这不是真的 福尔摩斯 不可能是真的!
It cannot be true, Holmes, it cannot!
没错 这不是真的
No, it can't.
- 锁上了吗?  - 就像之前布置的那样
- Is it locked?  - As per instruction.
那是窗户被打碎的声音 对吧?
That was a window breaking, wasn't it?
我们只需要关心一扇特定的窗户是否被打碎了
There's only one broken window we need concern ourselves with.
- 待在这里 华生  - 什么? 不行
- Stay here, Watson.  - What? No.
所有的门窗都已经锁上了
All the doors and windows to the house are locked.
这是他们唯一的出路 我需要你守在这!
This is their only way out, I need you here!
但那声音离得很近 肯定是从房子的这一侧传来的
But the sound was so close. It had to be from this side of the house.
待在这里!
Stay here!
哦!
Oh!
不!
No!
你说过会保证他的安全的 你保证过!
You promised to keep him safe. You promised!
你...
You...
你是人 我知道的
You're human, I know that.
你肯定是
You must be.
我们这样在黑暗中站着也没什么意思
Little use us standing here in the dark.
毕竟现在都是十九世纪了
After all, this is the 19th century.
请不要忘记我!
Do not forget me!
华生!
Watson!
- 她就在那! 就在那下面!  - 别告诉我你扔下那里不管了!
- She's there! She's down there!  - Don't tell me you abandoned your post!
什么? 福尔摩斯 她就在那里 我看见她了!
What? Holmes, she's there, I saw her!
没人了 都怪你!
Empty, thanks to you!
凶手跑了!
Our bird is flown!
不! 不 福尔摩斯 不是你想的那样的
No! No, Holmes, it wasn't what you think.
我看见她了! 她是鬼!
I saw her! The ghost!
根本就没有鬼!
There are no ghosts!
出什么事了? 尤斯塔斯爵士呢?
What happened? Where is Sir Eustace?
死了
Dead.
你要知道 这事真的不怪你
You really mustn't blame yourself, you know.
- 你说得对  - 很高兴你想明白了
- No, you're quite right.  - I'm glad you're seeing sense.
华生也有做的不对的地方
Watson is equally culpable.
我们本来可以破了这个案子的
Between us, we've managed to botch this whole case.
我答应过要保护好那个人的
I gave an undertaking to protect that man,
可是现在他却被一把匕首捅死了
now he's lying there with a dagger in his breast.
其实你是答应了要调查他的谋杀案
In fact, you gave an undertaking to investigate his murder.
我本来有信心 认为事情不会发展成这样!
In the confident expectation I would not have to!
你有什么发现吗 医生?
Anything you can tell us, Doctor?
杀他的人用了不小的力气
Well, he's been stabbed with considerable force.
- 所以凶手应该是个男人?  - 有可能
- It's a man, then?  - Possibly.
匕首非常锋利 所以也可能是女人吧?
A very keen blade, so it could conceivably have been a woman?
理论上讲 没错 但是我们知道凶手是谁了 我看到她了
In theory, yes, but we know who it was, I saw her.
- 华生!  - 我看到鬼了 我亲眼看到的!
- Watson!  - I saw the ghost, with my own eyes!
你什么都没看见! 你看见的是你以为应该看见的东西!
You saw nothing! You saw what you were supposed to see!
你自己都说了 我没什么想象力
You said yourself, I have no imagination.
那就动动脑子 排除所有不可能的情况 去观察剩下的线索
Then use your brain, such as it is, to eliminate the impossible,
在这个案子里 鬼就是不可能出现的情况
which in this case is the ghost, and observe what remains,
而剩下的线索就是破案的关键
which in this case is a solution
只需要简单的观察就行了 这可是雷斯垂德都会的事!
so blindingly obvious even Lestrade could work it out!
多谢!
Thank you!
别再想什么另一个世界的鬼怪了!
Forget spectres from the other world!
只有一个人有作案的动机和机会
There is only one suspect with motive and opportunity.
- 他们可能也会留下什么讯息  - 他们确实留下了信息
- They might as well have left a note.  - They did leave a note.
还有另一扇被打破的窗户
And then there's the matter of the other broken window.
- 什么另一扇窗户?  - 没错! 没有别的了
- What other broken window?  - Precisely! There isn't one.
只有我和华生进来的时候打破了一扇窗户
The only broken window is the one that Watson and I entered through,
可是 在那之前 我们确实听到了...
yet, prior to that, we distinctly heard the sound of...
- 你刚才说什么?  - 什么?
- What did you just say?  - Sorry?
讯息之类的 你刚才说什么来着?
About a note, what did you just say?
- 我说凶手确实留下了信息  - 没有啊
- I said the murderer did leave a note.  - No, they didn't.
匕首上系着一张留言 你没看见吗!
There's a message tied to the dagger. You must have seen it!
- 没有留言啊  - 有的!
- There's no message.  - Yes!
我发现尸体的时候并没有留言啊
There was no message when I found the body.
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
写了什么?
What is it?
你想吗?
Do you?
想什么?
Do I what?
你... 你是怎么拿到留言的?
How... how did you get that?
我把它留在犯罪现场了
I left it at the crime scene.
"犯罪现场"? 你从来学来的这些好听的说法
"Crime scene"? Where do you pick up these extraordinary expressions?
你想他吗?
Do you miss him?
莫里亚蒂已经死了
Moriarty is dead.
可是呢...?
And yet...?
他的尸体从来没被找到过
His body was never recovered.
对于一个被人推下瀑布的数学教授 这是有可能的
To be expected when one pushes a maths professor over a waterfall.
真实的理由常被戏剧性的表象所掩盖
Pure reason toppled by sheer melodrama.
你的生命也得以保全
Your life in a nutshell.
你是从哪学来的这些好听的说法?
Where do you pick up these extraordinary expressions?
你的体重又长了吗?
Have you put on weight?
你昨天才来看过我的 有可能吗?
You saw me only yesterday. Does that seem possible?
- 不可能  - 可是我的体重确实长了
- No.  - Yet here I am, increased.
由此可以看出 我们英国最优秀的侦探也不过如此吧?
What does that tell the foremost criminal investigator in England?
英国?
In England?
你陷得很深 夏洛克 比你想象的更深
You're in deep, Sherlock, deeper than you ever intended to be.
- 你列出清单了吗?  - 什么清单?
- Have you made a list?  - Of what?
所有的线索 我们需要一个清单
Everything. We will need a list.
真棒
Good boy.
不行 我还没写完
No, I haven't finished yet.
莫里亚蒂可能不会赞同
Moriarty may beg to differ.
他是在转移我的注意力 让我分心
He's trying to distract me. To derail me.
没错
Yes.
他就是透镜上的裂痕 粥里的老鼠屎
He's the crack in the lens, the fly in the ointment,
数据中的病毒
the virus in the data.
我要结束这一切
I have to finish this.
如果莫里亚蒂真的在莱辛巴赫瀑布死里逃生了的话
If Moriarty has risen from the Reichenbach cauldron,
他会自己找上门来的
he will seek you out.
那我就等着他
I'll be waiting.
好吧
Yes.
我猜你也会等他
I'm very much afraid you will.
他像这样已经两天了
Two days he's been like that.
- 他吃东西了吗?  - 没有 一口都没吃
- Has he eaten?  - No, not a morsel.
媒体今天都跑出来了 外面现在还有记者围着呢
Press are having a ruddy field day. There's still reporters outside.
他们一直在那待着 我赶都赶不走
Oh, they've been there all the time, I can't get rid of them.
我一直忙着给他泡茶
I've been rushed off my feet making tea.
你为什么要给他泡茶?
Why do you make him tea?
我也不知道 就是想这么做
I dunno, I just sort of do.
他说"只有一个嫌疑人" 然后就走了
He said, "There's only one suspect," and then he just walks away
什么也不肯解释
and now he won't explain.
这真奇怪 毕竟他挺喜欢这样的
Which is strange, because he likes that bit.
他还说这案子简单得我都能想明白
Said it was so simple I could solve it.
我确定他把事情夸大了
I'm sure he was exaggerating.
你觉得他在干什么呢?
What's he doing, do you think?
- 他说他在等待  - 等待什么?
- He says he's waiting.  - For what?
那个恶魔 我不觉得惊奇
The devil. I wouldn't be surprised.
在这里万事皆有可能
We get all sorts here.
- 有什么进展就发电报给我  - 好的
- Well, wire me if there's any change.  - Yeah.
我要说的话你都已经想到了
Everything I have to say has already crossed your mind.
那么我的答案你也许也想到了
Then possibly my answer has crossed yours.
就像一颗子弹
Like a bullet.
这个习惯很危险啊
It's a dangerous habit,
把手指扣在上膛的手枪扳机上 揣在晨衣口袋里
to finger loaded firearms in the pocket of one's dressing gown.
还是说你很高兴见到我呢?
Or are you just pleased to see me?
- 请原谅 我需要自我防卫  - 你不自我防卫才让我生气呢
- You'll forgive me for taking precautions.  - I'd be offended if you didn't.
很明显 出于礼貌我也有防卫
Obviously, I've returned the courtesy.
我喜欢你的房间 闻起来很有...
I like your rooms. They smell so...
男人味
manly.
我相信你早就对它够熟悉了吧
I'm sure you acquainted yourself with them before now.
对啊 你总不在家 出去斯特兰德大街上冒险
Well, you are always away, on your little adventures for The Strand.
告诉我 你会带着画师出门吗?
Tell me, does the illustrator travel with you?
推理的时候... 要不要摆个造型?
Do you have to pose... during your deductions?
我知道你趁我不在的时候
I'm aware of all six occasions you have visited these apartments
- 来过我的公寓六次  - 我知道你知道
- during my absence.  - I know you are.
顺便说一句 你的床真是舒适无比
By the way, you have a surprisingly comfortable bed.
你知不知道灰尘大部分是由人体皮肤组成的?
Did you know that dust is largely composed of human skin?
知道
Yes.
尝起来味道不一样 你得保持皮肤水分
Doesn't taste the same, though, you want your skin fresh.
- 有点脆  - 要坐下吗?
- Just a little crispy.  - Won't you sit down?
人们就是这样
That's all people really are, you know,
四处散布人体灰尘
dust waiting to be distributed.
弄得到处都是
And it gets everywhere. Ugh.
每呼吸一下 灰尘就在阳光下飞舞
In every breath you take, dancing in every sunbeam,
一群精疲力竭的人们
all the used-up people.
引人注目 我知道 你能坐...
Fascinating, I'm sure. Won't you sit...
人们 人们 人们! 总是弄脏身边的东西
People, people, people! Can't keep anything shiny.
你不介意我开枪吧?
Do you mind if I fire this?
清理一下枪膛
Just to clean it out.
没错 咱们别互相戏弄了
Exactly, let's stop playing.
我们不需要用玩具杀死对方
We don't need toys to kill each other.
- 那样就显示不出咱们的亲密了  - 坐下
- Where's the intimacy in that?  - Sit down.
- 为什么? 你想怎样?  - 你选择了来这里
- Why? What do you want?  - You chose to come here.
才不是 你知道不是这样
Not true, you know that's not true.
你想要什么 夏洛克?
What do you want, Sherlock?
真相
The truth.
这样啊 真相太无聊了!
That. Truth's boring!
你没想到我会在犯罪现场现身吧?
You didn't expect me to turn up at the scene of the crime, did you?
可怜的尤斯塔斯老爵士 报应来了挡不住
Poor old Sir Eustace. He got what was coming to him.
但是杀了他的不可能是你
But you couldn't have killed him.
那又怎样? 有什么大不了的? 省省吧 省省
Oh, so what? Does it matter? Stop it. Stop this.
你才不关心尤斯塔斯 那个新娘 什么都不关心
You don't care about Sir Eustace, or the Bride, or any of it.
整个案件勾起你兴趣的只有一件事
There's only one thing in this whole business that you find interesting.
我知道你在干什么
I know what you're doing.
新娘把枪放到嘴里打爆了半个脑袋
The Bride put a gun in her mouth and shot the back of her head off
然后又复活了
and then she came back.
不可能 但是她复活了
Impossible. But she did it.
你想知道她是怎么做到的
And you need to know how.
怎么做到的?
How?
没错吧?
Don't you?
不知道真相 搅得你心烦意乱
It's tearing your world apart, not knowing.
你在试图阻止我... 让我分心 误导我
You're trying to stop me... To distract me, derail me.
这案子不会让你联想到另外一个案子吗?
Because doesn't this remind you of another case?
这案子以前没发生过吗?
Hasn't this all happened before?
人世间的事总是翻来覆去 是哪一个案子?
There's nothing new under the sun. What was it?
哪一个? 哪一个案子呢?
What was it? What was that case? Huh?
你还记得吗?
Do you remember?
话已经到嘴边了 话已经到嘴边了
It's on the tip of my tongue. It's on the tip of my tongue.
话已经到嘴边了
It's on the tip of my tongue.
话已经到...
It's on the tip...
嘴边了
of my tongue.
为了哈德森太太的墙纸着想 我要提醒你一下
For the sake of Mrs. Hudson's wallpaper, I must remind you
一不小心动了手指 你就死定了
that one false move with your finger and you will be dead.
你说什么?
I'm sorry?
死亡... 才是性感新潮流
Dead... is the new sexy.
你猜怎么着 我的头脑清醒了不少
Well, I'll tell you what, that rather blows the cobwebs away.
- 你怎么可能会活着?  - 我看起来怎么样?
- How can you be alive?  - How do I look?
你说实话 这个伤口明显吗?
You can be honest, is it noticeable?
你的脑袋都炸开了 怎么还能活下来?
You blew your own brains out, how could you survive?
也许可以把头发朝上梳
Or maybe I could backcomb.
我看到你死了
I saw you die.
你为什么没死?
Why aren't you dead?
因为杀死你的不是瀑布 夏洛克
Because it's not the fall that kills you, Sherlock.
只有你才知道 不是瀑布
Of all people, you should know that, it's not the fall,
根本不是瀑布
it's never the fall.
是降落!
It's the landing!
我们已经降落了 先生 我们已经降落了
We've landed, sir. We've landed.
不 不 现在不行 现在不行!
No, no, not now, not now!
现在不行 现在不行
Not now, not now.
您的旅程很愉快吧 先生?
I trust you had a pleasant flight, sir?
旅程比我们想象的要短 亲爱的弟弟
Well, a somewhat shorter exile than we'd imagined, brother mine,
但考虑到您的强迫症 旅程也足够了
but probably adequate, given your levels of OCD.
- 我要回去!  - 什么?
- I have to go back!  - What?
我... 已经接近了 我已经接近答案了!
I was... I was nearly there, I nearly had it!
你到底在说什么?
What on earth are you talking about?
回去? 你根本没走多远
Go back where? You didn't get very far.
瑞可兰提和他那可恶的老婆! 你们听不懂吗?!
Ricoletti and his abominable wife! Don't you understand?!
我们当然听不懂 你根本就在胡扯 夏洛克
No, of course we don't, you're not making any sense, Sherlock.
这是个100年前的著名案件
It was a case, a famous one from 100 years ago.
保存在我的硬盘里 她看起来已经死了 但是又复活了
Lodged in my hard drive, she seemed to be dead, but then she came back.
什么 就像莫里亚蒂那样?
What, like Moriarty?
她对着头部开枪 完全和莫里亚蒂一样
Shot herself in the head, exactly like Moriarty.
但是你才刚知道
But you've only just been told.
我们也是刚刚才知道 现在电视上都在说他
We've only just found out, he's on every TV screen in the country.
是吗? 然后呢? 自从迈克罗夫特打电话来已经过了五分钟了
Yes? So? It's been five minutes since Mycroft called.
你们有什么进展吗? 你们都在干什么?
What progress have you made? What have you been doing?
更重要的是 你在干什么?
More to the point, what have YOU been doing?
我在我的思维宫殿里
I've been in my Mind Palace, of course.
当然
Of course.
我在进行思想实验 我如过在1895年的话
Running an experiment. How would I have solved the crime,
- 我会怎么破案  - 夏洛克啊
- if I'd been there in 1895?  - Oh, Sherlock.
所有的细节我都搞清楚了
I had all the details perfect.
我就在那里 一切都在 我沉浸在里面
I was there, all of it, everything. I was immersed.
当然如此
Of course you were.
你一直在读约翰的博客 你们相遇的故事
You've been reading John's blog. The story of how you met.
有时候用他的眼光看问题对我还是有帮助的
It helps me if I see myself through his eyes sometimes.
我聪明多了
I'm so much cleverer.
你觉得有谁会信你吗?
Do you really think anyone is believing you?
不 他会这个 我看他做过
No, he can do this, I've seen it.
思维宫殿 就好像他的脑海里有一整个世界
The Mind Palace, it's like a whole world in his head.
是的 我需要重新回去
Yes, and I need to get back there.
思维宫殿是一种记忆技巧 我知道它能用来做什么
The Mind Palace is a memory technique, I know what it can do
我也知道它肯定不能用来做什么
and I know what it most certainly cannot.
也许有几件事在我们两个之间只有我知道
Maybe there are one or two things that I know that you don't.
肯定有 你列清单了吗?
Oh, there are. Did you make a list?
你胖了不少 你的背心比外套要新
You've put on weight. That waistcoat is clearly newer than the jacket.
别说了! 别说了! 你列过清单了吗?!
Stop this! Just stop it! Did you make a list?!
什么清单?
Of what?
都要 夏洛克 你吸的所有东西
Everything, Sherlock. Everything you've taken.
不是那个 他有时候会出神 我看到过
No, it's not that, he goes into a sort of trance. I've seen him do it.
我和我弟弟有一个协议 自从那天起
We have an agreement, my brother and I, ever since that day.
不管我在哪里找到他 不管是小巷还是豪宅...
Wherever I find him, whatever back alley or doss-house...
他都能给我一个清单
there will always be a list.
他总不会花了五分钟就把那些全吸掉了吧
He couldn't have taken all that in the last five minutes.
- 他上飞机之前已经飘飘欲仙了  - 他看上去还挺正常的啊
- He was high before he got on the plane.  - He didn't seem high.
- 没有人比吸毒的人更会骗人  - 我没有成瘾 我只是随便吸吸
- Nobody deceives like an addict.  - I'm not an addict, I'm a user.
我用它来找点乐子 有时候帮助我思考
I alleviate boredom and occasionally heighten my thought processes.
天啊! 这些会杀了你的!
For God's sake! This could kill you!
- 你会死的!  - 有节制地吸毒就不会死了
- You could die!  - Controlled usage is not usually fatal
而且不吸毒也不代表永生
and abstinence is not immortality.
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提 我在搜索她
Emelia Ricoletti, I'm looking her up.
我也觉得应该查一下
Oh, I suppose we should.
我可以看得到军情五处的机密文件
I have access to the top level of the MI5 archive.
我看的就是那个
Yep, that's where I'm looking.
你觉得军情五处的安全系统怎么样?
What do you think of MI5 security?
要是有就好了
I think it would be a good idea.
艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提 "未解决" 他说得没错
Emelia Ricoletti, "unsolved", like he says.
你们能不能就闭嘴五分钟! 我必须要回去
Could you all just shut up for five minutes! I have to go back.
你来打扰我之前我已经快好了
I was nearly there before you stepped on and started yapping away!
"打扰?" 对不起 我们打扰到你了吗?
"Yapping?" Sorry, did we interrupt your session?
- 夏洛克 听我说  - 不 它只会鼓励你
- Sherlock, listen to me.  - No, it only encourages you.
- 我没生你的气  - 太好了!
- I'm not angry with you.  - Oh, that's a relief!
我还很怕... 等等 其实我一点都不担心
I was really worried... No, hold on, I really wasn't.
我以前也陪着你
I was there for you before.
我现在也会陪着你
I'll be there for you again.
我一直都会陪着你
I'll always be there for you.
这是我的错
This was my fault.
这和你没关系
It was nothing to do with you.
在监狱里待了一个礼拜 我应该早点注意到的
A week in a prison cell, I should have realised.
- 注意到什么?  - 你的情况是
- Realised what?  - That, in your case,
你一个人把自己锁起来 和你的宿敌在一起
solitary confinement is locking you up with your worst enemy.
- 天啊!  - 吗啡还是可卡因?
- Oh, for God's sake!  - Morphine or cocaine?
- 你说什么?  - 我什么都没说
- What did you say?  - I didn't say anything.
不 你说过 你说过...
No, you did, you said...
"今天是哪种? 吗啡还是可卡因"
"Which is it today? Morphine or cocaine."
"福尔摩斯?"
"Holmes?"
吗啡和可卡因... 你今天注射了哪种?
Morphine or cocaine... which is it today?
回答我 该死!
Answer me, damn it!
莫里亚蒂刚刚在这里
Moriarty was here.
莫里亚蒂已经死了
Moriarty's dead.
- 我刚刚在一架喷气式飞机上  - 什么?
- I was on a jet.  - A what?
你也在 还有迈克罗夫特
You were there, and Mycroft.
你没有离开过这个房间 福尔摩斯
You haven't left these rooms, Holmes.
你... 没有... 动过
You... haven't... moved.
好了 告诉我 吗啡还是可卡因?
Now, tell me, morphine or cocaine?
可卡因 7%的溶液
Cocaine. A 7% solution.
- 你想试试吗?  - 不想
- Would you care to try it?  - No.
不过我倒想找到剩下的那些药
But I would quite like to find every ounce of the stuff
然后把它们倒在外面
in your possession and pour it out of the window.
我应该阻止你的
I should be inclined to stop you.
那你就得记得了
Then you would be reminded, quite forcibly,
我们中谁是当兵的 谁是吸毒的
which of us is a soldier and which of us a drug addict.
你不是士兵 你是个医生
You're not a soldier, you are a doctor.
我是随军医生
I'm an army doctor,
我可以一边打烂你的骨头 一边叫出它们的名字
which means I could break every bone in your body while naming them.
亲爱的华生 你让情绪影响了你的判断力
My dear Watson, you are allowing emotion to cloud your judgment.
从来不在破案的时候吸毒
Never on a case.
你保证过我的 永远不在破案的时候吸毒
You promised me, never on a case.
不 我只是在你写的故事里这么说过
No, I just said that in one of your stories.
听着 我很乐意当你的丑角
Listen, I'm happy to play the fool for you.
我可以在你身边装成是个傻子
I will run along behind you like some halfwit,
让你看上去聪明一点 如果你需要这样的话
making you look clever, if that's what you need.
但是天啊 你得对自己要求高一点!
But dear God above, you will hold yourself to a higher standard!
- 为什么?  - 因为人们需要你这样
- Why?  - Because people need you to.
什么人 为什么? 是因为你那些白痴的故事吗?
What people, why? Because of your idiot stories?
是的 就是因为我那些"白痴的故事"
Yes, because of my "idiot stories".
福尔摩斯先生!
Mr. Holmes!
福尔摩斯先生 有电报 福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes, telegram, Mr. Holmes.
这是什么? 怎么了?
What is it? What's wrong?
- 是玛丽  - 玛丽? 她怎么了?
- It's Mary.  - Mary? What about her?
- 她很有可能有危险  - 有危险?
- It's entirely possible she's in danger.  - Danger?
- 没有时间浪费了  - 你是可卡因注射多了吗?
- There's not a moment to lose.  - Is this the cocaine talking?
玛丽能有什么危险?
What danger could Mary be in?
她应该是在拜访朋友吧
I'm sure she's just visiting with friends.
走了!
Come on!
出什么事了? 你现在清醒着吗?
What is happening? Are you even in a fit state?
玛丽出事了 当然清醒 不要怀疑 华生
For Mary, of course. Never doubt that, Watson.
不要怀疑我的神智
Never that.
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
我没事 我没事!
I'm fine. I'm fine!
别戴那个!
Not that one!
戴这个
This one.
- 为什么?  - 你是夏洛克・福尔摩斯 把这该死的帽子戴上
- Why?  - You're Sherlock Holmes. Wear the damn hat.
马车! 马车!
Cab! Cab!
告诉我 她在哪?
So tell me, where is she?
你必须告诉我 怎么回事?!
You must tell me, what's going on?!
行了 亲爱的华生!
Oh, good old Watson!
你什么时候能闭嘴不问问题?!
How would we fill the time if you didn't ask questions?!
夏洛克 快说我的老婆在哪里 你这自负的混蛋
Sherlock, tell me where my bloody wife is, you pompous prick,
不然我把你打开花!
or I'll punch your lights out!
福尔摩斯 她在哪?
Holmes, where is she?
在个不怎么神圣的教堂里
A de-sanctified church.
她觉得她找到答案了 而且没有更好的解释了
She thinks she's found the solution and, for no better reason than that,
她把自己处于了危境之中
she's put herself in the path of considerable danger.
真是会选妻子
What an excellent choice of wife.
见鬼?!
What the devil?!
我找到他们了
I've found them.
- 到底怎么回事 玛丽?  - 这里是他们的老巢 约翰
- What is all this, Mary?  - This is the heart of it all, John.
整个阴谋的核心
The heart of the conspiracy.
老天爷啊 这是个什么地方?
Great God, what is this place?
你到底在这里干什么?!
And what the devil are you doing here?!
我一直在查案
I've been making enquiries.
是福尔摩斯先生的指令
Mr. Holmes asked me.
福尔摩斯 你怎么能这样?
Holmes, how could you?
不是他 是聪明的那个
No, not him, the clever one.
很明显这个案子无法一个人实施
It seemed obvious to me that this business could not be managed alone.
我认为是有人帮了瑞可兰提夫人
My theory is that Mrs. Ricoletti had help.
是她的朋友们帮了她
Help from her friends.
- 干得漂亮 玛丽  - "聪明的那个?" 我...
- Bravo, Mary.  - "The clever one?" I...
我还以为我要失去你了
I thought I was losing you.
我以为我们...
I thought perhaps we were...
- 正在冷战  - 搬出去住的是你
- neglecting each other.  - Well, you're the one who moved out.
我在和玛丽说话
I was talking to Mary.
你在为迈克罗夫特做事?
You're working for Mycroft?
他喜欢照顾他那有点不正常的弟弟
He likes to keep an eye on his mad sibling.
然后就找了个间谍 你从没有怀疑过
And he had a spy to hand. Has it never occurred to you
你的妻子对于护士的职业过分娴熟吗?
your wife is excessively skilled for a nurse?
当然不会 因为他知道护士都有什么能力
Of course it hasn't, because he knows what a nurse is capable of.
- 你什么时候怀疑过?  - 大概只有现在吧
- When did it occur to you?  - Only now, I'm afraid.
当一个迟钝的弟弟一定很不好过吧
Must be difficult, being the slow little brother.
时间不等人 话说够了 干正事吧
Time I sped up. Enough chatter, let's concentrate.
对啊 这是怎么回事?
Yes, all right. What's all this about?
- 他们想要干什么?  - 去看看不就行了
- What do they want to accomplish?  - Why don't we go and find out.
抱歉! 看到锣我就手痒
Sorry! I can never resist a gong.
- 抗拒不了对戏剧的向往  - 真是想不到!
- Or a touch of the dramatic.  - Never have guessed!
看来大家和我一样努力
Though it seems you share my enthusiasm in that regard.
精彩绝伦
Excellent.
上好的演出
Superlative theatre.
真该为你们的表演鼓掌
I applaud the spectacle.
艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提朝自己开了枪
Emelia Ricoletti shot herself,
接着又从墓中复活 杀死了自己的丈夫
then apparently returned from the grave and killed her husband.
所以...
So...
怎么做到的呢?
how was it done?
让我来理一理事情经过
Let's take the events in order.
瑞可兰提夫人巧妙地吸引了所有人的注意
Mrs. Ricoletti gets everyone's attention in very efficient fashion.
你!
You!
你?!
You?!
还是我?
Or me?
她把一把左轮手枪放进了嘴里
She places one of the revolvers in her mouth,
实际上开的是朝向地面的那把枪
while actually firing the other into the ground.
一个同伙朝窗帘上泼出血液
An accomplice sprays the curtains with blood
因此楼下惊慌的众人
and thus her apparent suicide
见证了她的自杀
is witnessed by the frightened crowd below.
一具与瑞可兰提夫人非常相似的尸体
A substitute corpse, bearing a strong resemblance to Mrs. Ricoletti
代替了她的位置 并随后被转移到停尸间
takes her place and is later transported to the morgue,
小小的自杀案件不受伦敦警察局过多关注
a grubby little suicide of little interest to Scotland Yard.
与此同时 真正的瑞可兰提夫人溜走了
Meanwhile, the real Mrs. Ricoletti slips away.
接下来是最聪明的作案手段
Now comes the really clever part.
瑞可兰提夫人说服了一个认识她的马车夫
Mrs. Ricoletti persuaded a cab driver, someone who knew her,
去她丈夫常去的鸦片馆外拦住了他
to intercept her husband outside his favourite opium den.
在完美的舞台上完成了完美的表演
The perfect stage for a perfect drama.
你是谁? 你想怎样?
Who are you? What do you want?
艾米莉亚?
Emelia?
来人!
Help!
凶手指认确凿无比
A perfect positive identification.
这位瑞可兰提夫人从墓中爬了出来
The late Mrs. Ricoletti has returned from the grave
只需要一点点技术性的化妆
and a little skilled make-up
整个案件 只有复仇的鬼魂才说得通
and you have nothing less than the wrath of a vengeful ghost.
剩下只有一件事要做了
There was only one thing left to do.
快动手吧 不要哭
Swiftly now. No tears.
只需要把瑞可兰提夫人真正的尸体
All that remained was to substitute the real Mrs. Ricoletti
和停尸间里的替换即可
for the corpse in the morgue.
这时候 不管是谁去指认
This time, should anyone attempt to identify her,
那尸体绝对就是艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提
it would be positively, absolutely her.
但是她为什么那么做?
But why would she do that?
为了一具尸体而自杀?
Die to prove a point?
欲成一事必有牺牲
Every great cause has martyrs.
每场战争必有敢死之行 没错 这是一场战争
Every war has suicide missions and make no mistake, this is war.
一半的人类都在这个军队中对抗着另一半
One half of the human race at war with the other.
一只看不见的军队在我们身边徘徊
The invisible army hovering at our elbow,
支撑着我们的家园
tending to our homes,
抚养着我们的后代
raising our children.
被无视 被施舍
Ignored, patronised,
被漠视
disregarded.
连选举权都不允许享有
Not allowed so much as a vote.
尽管如此 一个军队
But an army nonetheless,
已抱着最大的善意准备崛起
ready to rise up in the best of causes.
去匡正那些如人性本身一般古老的不公
To put right an injustice as old as humanity itself.
你明白了吧 华生 迈克罗夫特是对的
So you see, Watson, Mycroft was right.
这一战我们必败
This is a war we must lose.
她快死了
She was dying.
- 谁?  - 艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提
- Who was?  - Emelia Ricoletti.
她有很明显的肺结核表征
There were clear signs of consumption...
我怀疑她原本就时日不多了
I doubt she was long for this world.
所以她决定让自己死得其所
So she decided to make her death count.
她对美国的秘密社团已经很熟悉了
She was already familiar with the secret societies of America.
她也有能力用她们惊吓
And was able to draw on their methods of fear
和恐惧的方式公开地
and intimidation to publicly, very publicly,
让尤斯塔斯・卡迈克尔直面自己过去的罪恶
confront Sir Eustace Carmichael with the sins of his past.
他是在美国认识她的
He knew her out in the States.
向她承诺了一切
Promised her everything.
婚姻 地位
Marriage, position.
然后他占有了她...
And then he had his way with her...
又把她抛弃了
and threw her over.
令她孓然一人 身无分文
Left her abandoned and penniless.
琥珀!
Hooper!
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
我得说一句 福尔摩斯 她可没糊弄到我
For the record, Holmes, she didn't have me fooled.
你为什么从来没提起过我呢 先生?
Why do you never mention me, sir?
艾米莉亚以为她会在瑞可兰提那里找到幸福
Emelia thought that she'd found happiness with Ricoletti,
但是他也是一个畜生
but he was a brute too.
艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提是我们的朋友
Emelia Ricoletti was our friend.
你不知道那个混蛋是怎么对她的
You have no idea how that bastard treated her.
但是那个新娘 福尔摩斯 我们看到她了
But the Bride, Holmes, we saw her.
是的 华生 我们确实看到了
Yes, Watson, we did.
玻璃碎裂的声音是吗?
The sound of breaking glass?
并不是窗户
Not a window,
只是一个老式的剧场小伎俩
just an old theatrical trick.
- 不可能 福尔摩斯 这不可能  - 不 这不可能
- It cannot be true, Holmes, it cannot!  - No, it can't.
这叫做佩珀尔幻象
It's called Pepper's Ghost.
简单地在玻璃上反射出活人的影像
A simple reflection in glass of a living, breathing person.
她们犯下的唯一错误就是在移动它的时候把它打碎了
Their only mistake was breaking the glass when they removed it.'
看看你们周围
Look around you.
这间屋子里全是新娘
This room is full of brides.
一旦她要出现
Once she had risen,
任何人都可以是她
anyone could be her.
那个复仇的鬼魂
The avenging ghost.
晴天霹雳般的恐惧直射进
A legend to strike terror into the heart of any man
恶意满满的男人心里
with malicious intent.
一个纠缠那些未受惩罚
A spectre to stalk those unpunished brutes
却早该遭末日审判的畜生的鬼魂
whose reckoning is long overdue.
复仇女神的联盟觉醒了
A league of furies awakened.
我...
The women I...
我们欺骗 背叛过的女人
we have lied to, betrayed.
我们无视或者贬低过的女人
The women we have ignored and disparaged.
一旦这个念头出现
Once the idea exists,
就无法消除
it cannot be killed.
这是一心一意的人才能干出的事
This is the work of a single-minded person.
一个最直接感知尤斯塔斯精神虐待的人
Someone who knew first-hand about Sir Eustace's mental cruelty.
这个幽暗的秘密
The dark secret,
只有她最亲密的朋友们知道
kept from all but her closest friends,
包括艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提...
including Emelia Ricoletti...
她丈夫多年前对不住的女人
the woman her husband wronged all those years before.
如果一个人不理会鬼魂
If one disregards the ghost,
那么就只有一个嫌疑人
there is only one suspect.
对吗 卡迈克尔夫人?
Isn't that right, Lady Carmichael?
然而有一个小细节我不是很明白
One small detail doesn't quite make sense to me, however.
为什么要让我阻止一个你想要犯下的罪行?
Why engage me to prevent a murder you intended to commit?
嗯?
Hmm?
说不怎么通啊 说不怎么通啊
Doesn't quite make sense, doesn't quite make sense.
当然说不通 并不是真的
Of course it doesn't make sense, it's not real.
夏洛克
Oh, Sherlock.
躲猫猫
Peek-a-boo.
不
No.
不 不是你
No, not you.
不可能是你
It can't be you.
来嘛 严肃点嘛
I mean, come on, be serious.
服装 铜锣?
The costumes, the gong?
作为一个犯罪大师
Speaking as a criminal mastermind,
我们实际上并没有铜锣或者特殊的服装
we don't really have gongs or special outfits.
到底发生了什么事?
What the hell is going on?
这对你来说够蠢了吗?
Is this silly enough for you yet?
够哥特吗? 对你来说够疯狂吗?
Gothic enough? Mad enough, even for you?
说不通啊 夏洛克 因为并不是真的
It doesn't make sense, Sherlock, because it's not real.
- 一个都不是  - 他在说什么?
- None of it.  - What's he talking about?
因为这些都是你想象出来的
This is all in your mind.
夏洛克?
Sherlock?
福尔摩斯!
Holmes!
你在做梦
You're dreaming.
他在做梦吗?
Is he dreaming?
醒过来了
And there he is.
有那么一会儿 还以为我们要失去你了
Thought we'd lost you for a moment.
我可以检查下吗 这就是你说的"控制用量"?
May I just check, is this what you mean by "controlled usage"?
艾米莉亚・瑞可兰提夫人 我必须知道她埋在哪里
Mrs. Emelia Ricoletti, I need to know where she was buried.
- 什么 120年前?  - 是的
- What, 120 years ago?  - Yes.
哪怕记录存在的话 也得找好几个星期呢
That would take weeks to find, if those records even exists.
- 就算是用我的资源  - 找到了
- Even with my resources.  - Got it.
我不明白 这有什么关联嘛?
I don't get it, how is this relevant?
我必须知道自己是正确的 这样我才能确信
I need to know I was right, then I'll be sure.
- 你是指莫里亚蒂是怎么做到的吗?  - 是的
- You mean how Moriarty did it?  - Yes.
但是这些统统没有发生 全是你想象出来的
But none of that really happened, it was in your head.
我在大脑中调查排演
My investigation was the fantasy,
案件发生如我所料
the crime happened exactly as I explained.
墓碑是她的一群朋友立的
The stone was erected by a group of her friends.
我不知道你在这能查出什么
I don't know what you think you'll find here.
我要试一试!
I need to try!
瑞可兰提夫人是埋在这的 那另外一个呢?
Mrs. Ricoletti was buried here, but what happened to the other one?
那具代替她"自杀"的尸体呢?
The corpse they substituted for her after the so-called suicide?
- 当然被他们移走了  - 但是去哪了?
- They'd move it, of course they would.  - But where?
肯定不是在这
Well, not here.
但是... 这事一定得有人去做
But that... That's exactly what they must have done.
作案者们一定有内应帮他们
The conspirators had someone on the inside.
他们找到了一具尸体 就好比那次茉莉・琥珀给我找了一具...
They found a body, just like Molly Hooper found a body for me, when...
好吧 这事就不用再说一遍了
Yeah, well, we don't need to go into all that again, do we?
你不会真想这么做吧?
You're not seriously going to do this?
要不然我们来这里干什么 我得知道真相
It's why we came here. I need to know.
典型的瘾君子症状
Spoken like an addict.
- 这对我很重要!  - 不 这说明你需要治疗!
- This is important to me!  - No, this is you needing a fix.
- 约翰...  - 莫里亚蒂回来了
- John...  - Moriarty's back.
咱们还有案子 当下有个真真实实的问题存在着
We have a case, we have a real-life problem right now.
我知道 这事等一下解决 我要先把这事做好
Getting to that, it's next on the list. Just let me do this.
不 大家总是随你想干什么就干什么
No, everyone always lets you do whatever you want.
- 所以你才会变成这样!  - 约翰 拜托了...
- That's how you got in this state!  - John, please...
这次我不干了 夏洛克 我不干了!
I'm not playing this time, Sherlock. Not any more!
等你准备开始工作了 再联系我
When you're ready to go to work, give me a call.
- 我要带玛丽回家了  - 你要干什么?
- I'm taking Mary home.  - You're what?
- 玛丽带我回家  - 这还差不多
- Mary's taking me home.  - Better.
- 他说得对  - 他对又怎样?!
- He's right, you know.  - So what if he's right?!
他总是有道理 有什么意思!
He's always right, it's boring!
你会帮我吗?
Will you help me?
找出那个女人
Cherchez la femme.
瞧瞧呀
Oh, dear.
空空如也
The cupboard is bare.
他们一定埋在下面了
They must have buried it underneath.
他们一定是埋在棺材下面了
They must have buried it underneath the coffin.
运气不好啊 夏洛克
Bad luck, Sherlock.
也许他们用了别的办法处理尸体
Maybe they got rid of the body in another way.
很有可能
No... More than likely.
不管怎样 这是很久以前的事了
At any rate, it was a very long time ago.
我们确实还有更要紧的事要做 兄弟
We do have slightly more pressing matters to hand, little brother.
莫里亚蒂? 死而复生?
Moriarty? Back from the dead?
# 请不要忘记我 #
# Do not forget me. #
# 请不要忘记我! #
# Do not forget me! #
这里?
This?
我明白了
Oh, I see.
我还没醒呢?
Still not awake, am I?
太深了 夏洛克 实在太深了
Too deep, Sherlock, way too deep.
恭喜 你将成为史上第一个
Congratulations, you will be the first man in history
被埋葬在自己记忆宫殿的人
to be buried in his own Mind Palace.
这个背景设置有点夸张了 不是吗?
The setting is a shade melodramatic, don't you think?
对于你和我来说?
For you and me?
一点都不夸张
Not at all.
你到底是什么人?
What are you?
你知道我是什么人
You know what I am.
我是莫里亚蒂
I'm Moriarty.
犯罪界的拿破仑
The Napoleon of Crime.
- 莫里亚蒂已经死了!  - 在你的心里可没死
- Moriarty's dead!  - Not in your mind.
在那里我永远不会死
I'll never be dead there.
你有次把你的大脑叫做硬盘
You once called your brain a hard drive.
那就和我这个病毒打个招呼吧
Well, say hello to the virus.
这就是咱俩的结局
This is how we end, you and I.
永远在这里
Always here,
永远在一起
always together.
你有个精妙绝伦的大脑 莫里亚蒂
You have a magnificent brain, Moriarty.
我很欣赏
I admire it.
我承认你的大脑甚至比得上我自己的大脑
I concede it may even be the equal of my own.
我很感动
I'm touched.
我很荣幸
I'm honoured.
但是说到在悬崖边缘
But when it comes to the matter of unarmed combat
徒手搏斗...
on the edge of a precipice...
你才是掉进瀑布的那一个
you're going in the water,
小矮个
short-arse.
你觉得你很高大强壮吗 夏洛克!
Oh, you think you're so big and strong, Sherlock!
我可不这么想
Not with me.
我是你的弱点!
I am your weakness!
我压制了你!
I keep you down!
你的每一次差错 每一次失败
Every time you stumble, every time you fail,
在你虚弱之时
when you're weak,
我... 就...
I... am...
出现了!
there!
不
No,
别想挣扎了
don't try to fight it.
躺好接受失败!
Lie back and lose!
要不要一起跳下去?
Shall we go over together?
永远在一起 不是吗?
It has to be together, doesn't it?
结局永远都是你
At the end it's always just you
还有我!
and me!
教授 如果你不介意离我的朋友远一点的话
Professor, if you wouldn't mind stepping away from my friend,
他应该不会觉得你那么烦人了
I do believe he finds your attention a shade annoying.
这不公平 你们有两个人!
That's not fair, there's two of you!
我们两个总是在一起 你难道没看过杂志上连载的故事吗?
There's always two of us. Don't you read The Strand?
跪下 教授
On your knees, Professor.
双手抱头
Hands behind your head.
多谢了 约翰
Thank you, John.
你从什么时候开始叫我约翰了?
Since when do you call me John?
你会感到吃惊的
You'd be surprised.
那倒不会
No, I wouldn't.
你该醒过来了 夏洛克
Time you woke up, Sherlock.
我是写故事的人 我在故事里的时候 自己会知道的
I'm a story-teller, I know when I'm in one.
没错
Of course.
你当然会知道 约翰
Of course you do, John.
那么 他是什么样的?
So what's he like?
另一个世界里的另一个我?
The other me in the other place?
比看起来要聪明
Smarter than he looks.
那就是非常聪明了
Pretty damn smart, then.
确实非常聪明
Pretty damn smart.
天啊 你们俩怎么不干脆私奔了算了!
Ugh, why don't you two just elope, for God's sake?!
这话太难听了
Impertinent.
我也觉得被冒犯了
Offensive.
你介不介意我来处理?
Actually, would you mind?
当然不介意
Not at all.
- 也该轮到我了  - 确实
- It was my turn.  - Quite so.
你打算怎么醒过来?
So how do you plan to wake up?
呃...
Oh...
我想应该这样
I should think like this.
你确定吗?
Are you sure?
和你在一起的时候 我总能死里逃生
Between you and me, John, I always survive a fall.
可是要怎么做?
But how?
用演绎法 亲爱的华生
Elementary, my dear Watson.
- 想我了吗?  - 夏洛克 你还好吗?
- Miss me?  - Sherlock, are you all right?
当然了 为什么会不好?
Yes. Of course I am, why wouldn't I be?
因为你可能用药过量了 你应该去医院
Because you probably just OD'd. You should be in hospital.
没时间了
Hm, no time.
我必须马上回贝克街 莫里亚蒂又出现了
I have to go to Baker Street now, Moriarty's back.
如果他能让你别吸毒了 我倒是有点希望他回来了
I almost hope he is, if it'll save you from this.
不需要这个了 还有更实际的案子等着我
No need for that now, I've got the real thing.
- 我还有工作  - 夏洛克...
- I have work to do.  - Sherlock...
答应我
promise me.
你还在这里干什么?
What are you still doing here?
你难道不应该像个懂事的哥哥一样
Shouldn't you be off getting me a pardon or something,
去给我弄个赦免令之类的吗?
like a proper big brother?
华生医生...
Dr. Watson...
请照顾好他
look after him.
拜托了
Please.
夏洛克 等等 你解释一下 莫里亚蒂还活着吗?
Sherlock, hang on, explain. Moriarty's alive, then?
我从来没说他还活着 我说他又出现了
I never said he was alive, I said he was back.
所以他死了?
So he's dead?
他当然死了 他对着自己的脑袋开了枪 没人能在那种情况下活下来
Of course he's dead, he blew his own brains out, no-one survives that.
我刚刚以过量用药为代价证明了这一点
I just went to the trouble of an overdose to prove it.
毫无疑问 莫里亚蒂已经死了
Moriarty is dead, no question.
但是更重要的是 我清楚地知道他下一步要做什么
But more importantly, I know exactly what he's going to do next.
飞行器
Flying machines,
还有 呃 叫电话的通信装置?
these, er, telephone contraptions?
这也太疯狂了吧?
What sort of lunatic fantasy is that?
这仅仅是我对未来世界 以及对你和我在那个世界所扮演的角色的
It was simply my conjecture of what a future world might look like
简单的设想
and how you and I might fit inside it.
懂逻辑的人能够通过一滴水推断出
From a drop of water a logician should be able to infer
它来自大西洋还是尼亚加拉河
the possibility of an Atlantic or a Niagara.
又或是莱辛巴赫大瀑布?
Or a Reichenbach?
你写完这个案子了吗?
Have you written up your account of the case?
- 写完了  - 嗯
- Yes.  - Hmm.
你会把它写成是我为数不多的失败吧?
Modified to put it down as one of my rare failures, of course?
当然
Of course.
就叫做...
The Adventure Of...
无形的军队
The Invisible Army.
复仇女神的联盟?
The League Of Furies?
魔鬼军团?
The Monstrous Regiment?
我觉得 不如叫做"可恶的新娘"
I rather thought The Abominable Bride.
有点惊悚的感觉
A trifle lurid.
这样销量才好 毕竟里面也有谋杀的内容
It'll sell. It's got proper murders in it too.
这方面你是专家
You're the expert.
在现实状态里
As for your own tale,
你服用的真的只是百分之七的溶液吗?
are you sure it's still just a 7% solution that you take?
我觉得你可能增加了剂量
I think you may have increased the dosage.
或许那也是我的幻觉
Perhaps I was being a little fanciful.
不过这种事情也时有发生
But perhaps such things could come to pass.
在任何时候 我都知道在那样的世界里我也能很自在
In any case, I know I would be very much at home in such a world.
- 哈 我可不这么觉得  - 我很怀疑
- Huh, I don't think I would be. - I beg to differ.
不过我一直明白 我从来都是个与时代格格不入的人
But then I've always known I was a man out of his time.